<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ouerthrow of the iustification of workes and of the vain doctrin of the merits of men with the true affection of the iustification of faith and of the good workes that procead or come of the same, and in what respect our good workes are crouned or rewarded of God settte foorth dialoge wise by John Veron</title>
            <author>Véron, John, d. 1563.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1561</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 182 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14367</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24685</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112540</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847788</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847788</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12849</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14367)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12849)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1612:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ouerthrow of the iustification of workes and of the vain doctrin of the merits of men with the true affection of the iustification of faith and of the good workes that procead or come of the same, and in what respect our good workes are crouned or rewarded of God settte foorth dialoge wise by John Veron</title>
                  <author>Véron, John, d. 1563.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 74, [6] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Newlye set foorthe and alowed accordynge to the order appoynted in the Quenes maiesties iniunctions [by Ihon Tysdale],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1561.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: The iustification of faythe.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Justification --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12849:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The ouer throw of the iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of workes and of the vain doctrin of the merits of men, with the true aſſertion of the iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of faith and of the good workes that procead or come of the ſame, and in what reſpect our good workes are crouned or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded of God ſette foorth dialoge wiſe by Iohn Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.</bibl> Ye are ſaued by grace, and that throughe fayth, not of your ſelues, it is the gyfte of God not of workes, leaſt any man ſhoulde glorye.</q>
            <p>¶Newlye ſet foorthe and alowed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to the order appoynted in the Quenes maieſties iniunctions. Ano. 1561.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12849:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT</hi> honorable, Syr Iames Blount knight, Lord Mont ioy &amp;c. Iohn Veron wiſheth grace, peace of conſcience, and encreaſe of Godlye honoure, frome God the father, throughe his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere haue I added, right honourable Lorde, vnto my treatiſes of predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and of free wyll, a ſmall booke, whiche I haue entituled: The ouer throwe of the iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of workes, and of the vayne doctryne of the merites of men, with the true aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the iuſtification of fayeth, and of the good workes that do proceade of the ſame, and in what reſpecte our good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes are rewarded or crouned of God: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that theſe doctrines, do ſo depende one of an other, that they can in no wyſe be ſeparated, or put a ſunder, onleſſe we wyll wante the perfecte vnderſtandinge of them all, and ſo be blynde ſtyll in the cheyfeſt and moſte principall poyntes of oure relygion. Of predeſtination, howe
<pb facs="tcp:12849:2"/> frutefull and neceſſarye the doctrine of it, is, what ſo euer the ſwyniſhe gruntynge Epicures, and carnall worldelinges, doth ſaye to the contrary, I wyl ſpeake nothing nowe at this preſente, becauſe that I am fullye determined, by the healpe and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce of the holye ſpirite of God, ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to ſet foorthe an Apologye or defence of my doctrine, touchinge that poynte of our religion, beyng directed to the quenes maieſtye, vnto whome the treatyſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is dedicated. Neyther do I nede great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to ſpeake of the doctrine of free wyll ſythe that in the ſettinge foorthe of it, I haue ſo tempered my ſtyle, that I kepte my ſelfe alwayes within the lymites and boundes of Gods worde, goinge neyther on the ryghte nor on the lefte hande, but walkinge ſtyll in that moſt ſure and plain hyghe waye, that the Patriarches, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phettes, and Apoſtels, wyth the Godlye aunciente wryters of the primitiue church had alreadye trodden or beaten vnto vs. Many obiections of the Popepelagians, and free wyllmen of our tyme, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer were touched before, haue I fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in it, as it ſhall playnlye appeare vnto them, that wyll wyth a ſyngle eye, and with an vprighte iudgement, reade the whole treatiſe. The only marke that I ſhoote at in all theſe woorkes, is that the grace of God, maye be throughlye mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, and the vayne gloryinge of men, in theyr owne ſtrength, which all thinges
<pb facs="tcp:12849:3"/> beynge rightly conſidered, and diligently wayed, is nothinge at al) beinge taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye, the whole glorye of oure ſaluation ſhuld be geuen only vnto the mercy &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of our heauenly father<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who as by the death paſſion &amp; bloudſhedding of his ſon Ieſu Chriſt, doeth fully ſaue vs, ſo by his holye ſpirit he doeth regenerate vs, and takinge awaye our ſtony heartes from vs, he geueth vs fleſhy hearts, that is obedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente and treatable: he maketh vs of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyllinge, wyllinge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the bounde ſlaues of ſynne, the ſeruauntes of his ſonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Chriſt, for to ſerue him in holyneſſe and righteouſneſſe all the dayes of oure lyfe, and ſo brynginge vs in to the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the children of God (for where the ſpirit of the Lord is, there is fredome) he maketh vs to walke in thoſe good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, that he hath prepared for vs to walke in. Neyther can it iuſtely be ſayed, that eyther in my booke of predeſtination, or in my booke of free wyll, I did miniſter to any man occaſion, eyther to lyue lycen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſlye, aſthough it made no matter how they lyue, that are by the immutable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of God, ordayned vnto lyfe euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge, or to beſlacke in doynge of thoſe good woorkes, that are required of vs in Goddes booke. Whiche all menne ſhall moſte euidently ſee (excepte they wyll be wylfullye blinde) by this booke, that now at this preſent, I haue ſet foorth, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated
<pb facs="tcp:12849:3"/> vnto your honourable Lordſhip, whom I ſee of all men to be moſt earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye geuen vnto good letters, and moſte principally to the ſtudy of the holy and ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cred ſcriptures. Which, as it is a thinge verye rare amonge the greateſt part of the noble men of our tyme: ſo wyl it be a moſt precious ornamente, bothe to you, and to to the honourable ſtocke that ye come of. For, what greater co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendacion can there be to ſuche as ye are, than to haue a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and vnderſtandinge of the liberall ſciences, and of the tonges, that they be written in: and ſpecially to be ſo acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wyth the infallible worde of God, the onlye Antidotus or conterpoyſon, againſt all venimous ſects and hereſyes, that ye ſhal at all tymes be able mightely to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande all falſe and erroneous doctrines, that by the procuremente of Sathane the deuyll the enemye of oure ſaluation, haue heretofore ryſen and doo daylye ryſe in Chriſtes church? I do here let paſſe, how muche good ye wyll do by youre good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, vnto thoſe that are of the baſſeſte ſort, when they ſee your Lordſhip to be ſo ſeriouſly geuen, to ſuche vertuous excerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. it wyll be an wonderfull encorage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente vnto them: and vnto the other, that be of the ſame degree that ye are of, or of an higher, a marueylous prickinge forre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes. For, if ther be any ſparke or drop of Godly ſhamefaſtenes in them they wil bluſhe and be aſhamed, when they ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:12849:4"/> heare you grauely and learnedly to reaſon of highe matters of learninge and of the principall poynts of our religion, to ſtand lyke domme and paynted ymages, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſaye nothinge. Therfore go on ſtyll, as ye haue Godlye begonne: beinge moſt ſure, that he which hath of his free mercy and goodneſſe begonne this good worke in you, by his holy ſpirit ſtyrring vp your hearte to ſuch Godly ſtudyes: wyll ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye performe it, and bringe to ſuche a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect end that it wyl be not onely to your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtinge comforte, but alſo to the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable vtility vnd profit of your own naturall contrey. I woulde haue declared brieflye, what be the chiefeſt poyntes, that I do entreate of in this my boke, but becauſe that the argumente of it, is ſet foorth afore the beginninge of the whole woorke, I haue thought it vnneceſſarye. Here therfore, wyll I make an ende, moſt humblye beſechinge your good Lordſhip too take this my ſymple laboure in good parte, not ſo much conſideringe the ſmall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the gyfte, as the heart, and pure good wyll or zeale of the geuer. Thus the eternal and euerlaſting god preſerue bothe youre good Lordſhippe, and my good ladye youre wyfe, wyth all youre Godlye famylye and houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:12849:4"/>
            <head>¶The argument of the whole boke.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Yrſte and foremoſte we haue declared, that we are freelye iuſtified, that is to ſay, deliuered from ſynne, eternall dampnation and euerlaſtinge death, and coumpted righteouſe in the ſyghte of God, through fayth only in our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt, without any merits or deſeruynges, goynge before. Which thinge hathe bene mooſte ſtrongly proued both by manyfeſt and playne texts of the ſcriptures, and alſo by the autoryties of the aunciente fathers of the primitiue churche, contrarye to the ſklaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous and moſt lyinge reportes of the enemyes of the truth, which do, moſt vngodlye blowe abroade, that we haue of late dayes ſucked out thys doctrine of oure fyngers endes, not one af the olde writers ſaying once: <hi>Sola fides iuſtificat:</hi> faith
<pb facs="tcp:12849:5"/> onely or fayeh alone doth iuſtifye. But how falſe this their report is, ye ſhal be iudges your ſelues, after ye haue reade the whole worke.</p>
            <p>We dyd, almooſte in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynninge of this diſputation, leaſt anye impedimente or let ſhould be lefte vnto the reader, concile Paul and Iames together, where, vnto the ignoraunt, they dyd ſeme to diſagree, whiche (I truſte) is ſo ſubſtantiallye done, that any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable man, wyll holde him ſelf ſatiſfyed. Secondlye it hath bene ſhewed, that as all the works, that we do afore oure iuſtification, I meane, afore we be graffed in Chriſt, and throughe fayth made members of his bodye, althoughe they ſeme neuer ſo glorious, ſo per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fect and excellent, yet are but mere ſynne, and abhomination in the ſyght of God: ſo after we be once iuſtifyed, and made lyuely braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of that true vyne, we muſt not remain harein and vnfruteful
<pb facs="tcp:12849:5"/> trees, but bringe foorth the frutes of our fayth, and abounde or flow in all kinde of good woorkes that God hath prepared for vs to walk in, remembring that we are ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto created in Chriſt Ieſus, who hath redemed vs, and clenſed from our ſyns, to the end that we ſhuld be a peculiar people vnto him, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtlye geuen vnto good workes. Here haue we by the waye, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen wyll workes, that is ſuch maner of works, as are ſet foorth by the mere inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion of man, with out anye ſure ground or foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Gods boke, or wythout any promyſſe conteyned in the ſame, prouinge, that all ſuche workes, for as muche, as they bee done withoute fayeth, canne in no wyſe pleaſe god, but are an abominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto him, althoughe they be done, as they doe commonlye terme it, of a good intente and ſo, vppon occaſion, we haue declared, and made manifeſt and playne, by the
<pb facs="tcp:12849:6"/> hiſtoryes of Nadab and Abihu, of Saule, and of Dauid in bringinge the Arke in to Ieruſalem, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than God had ordayned, how perilous a thinge it is, to attempte any thinge of good intente, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſure warant of gods word, in the religion, worſhipping, &amp; ſeruice of God. Thyrdlye we teach what be thoſe workes that are to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for good works, euen ſuch as God doeth expreſſelye comaunde vs in his worde. Which are moſte liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet foorth vnto vs in manye pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the old and new Teſtament. How be it, this leſſon is alſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, that al they that do thoſe good workes (althoughe they be neuer ſo good workes in them ſelues) do not by and by deſerue, the comen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and prayſe of well doinge in the ſight of God, eyther becauſe that they do them, to the end that they may be glorified of menne, or for reward ſake, the hope wherof beinge taken awaye they woulde
<pb facs="tcp:12849:6"/> not as muche, as geue a cuppe of colde water, or for feare of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhemente after this lyfe, and not for the loue onely, that they beare to God, and to theyr neighboure, or for to ſhew their obedience, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes his wyl and commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. But for the better inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the ignoraunt, we haue ſet foorth at large, all the chiefe and pryncipall cauſes that oughte to moue vs, to do good woorkes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe we looked for no rewarde at all at Goddes hande, who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandinge wyll not leaue our good workes vncrowned or vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, firſt becauſe that we haue throughe ſayeth, felowſhip with his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, whoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte obedience, he imputeth vnto vs for our owne, therbye moſt am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plye and aboundantly ſupplying, what ſoeuer is wantinge and lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge in vs. Secondlye becauſe, that he hathe made him ſelfe deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour vnto vs not by receauing any
<pb facs="tcp:12849:7"/> thinge of vs, but by promiſſing all thinges, as ſaint Auguſtine doeth witneſſe. Here alſo are the cauſes ſhewed, why oure good workes, althoughe in them ſelues, they be full of imperfection, do pleaſe God and are acceptable vnto him, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ought to be vnto vs a great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coragemente to lyue Godlye, and to excerciſe our ſelues in all maner of good workes, that God hathe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded vs in his word, beinge ſure, that we canne not but pleaſe him in ſo doing. And as for merits it hath ben moſte ſtrongly proued, that althoughe we were able to do what ſoeuer God hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded vs, yet we oughte to reckenne our ſelues vnprofitable ſeruauntes, &amp; that we haue done but our dutye. But for as muche as no man is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to doo the tenth parte of Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements, with ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection as God doth require, what do we merit or deſerue (if our wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes be examined after the ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:12849:7"/> of Gods iudgement,) but the endeleſſe tormentes of hell fyer? Laſte of all, concerninge the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of glorye after thys life, it hathe bene ſufficientelye declared and ſhewed, that there can be no ſuch diuerſities or degrees of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, by reaſon of any merites, but that if therebe any, it commeth of the mere mercye and goodneſſe of God, who doeth in vs moſte libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally croune his owne giftes. The chefe ſcope or marke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhote at in ſettinge foorth of this doctrine, is: that we hauing learned whence our ſaluation doeth come, ſhoulde geue the whole glorye thereof, to the onely mercye and goodneſſe of God declared vnto vs in his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, and moſt ſurely ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vp by his bloude. To whome wyth the father, and the holye ghoſt be all prayſe, glorye, and honoure, worldes wythoute ende. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:12849:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12849:8"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>The ouer throwe of the iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of workes, and of the vayne and found doctrine of the meryts of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with the true aſſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the iuſtification of faith, &amp; of the good workes, that do procede and come of theſame, and in what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte they be crowned or rewarded of God, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoorthe Dialoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by Ihon Veron,</head>
            <list>
               <head>The names of the ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dydimus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Eutrapelus</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Albion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Philalethes.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYdimus:</speaker>
               <p>Syth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we haue already ſufficiently ſpoken of the doctrine of predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, of the diuyne prouydence
<pb facs="tcp:12849:9"/> of God and of free wyll, I am of opinion, that it were good to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate ſomewhat of the iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of faythe, and of the good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes that do ſpring and come of the ſame. For manye there be which when they heare that we be iuſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by fayth onely, withoute the workes of the law, ſtreight waies do crye out, that they nede not to do good woorkes, yea that it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no matter how they liue, ſo that they beleue onelye.<note place="margin">The blaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phemers of the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of faythe.</note> I woulde fayne, that by ſettinge foorth this matter playnely, as ye haue done the other, the mouthes of ſuche blaſphemours myghte ones bee ſtopped.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPELVS.</speaker>
               <p>That, whiche ye ſaye, good neyghbour, maye rather be wyſhed than ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped or loked for.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The mali<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciouſneſſe of the ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mies of the truth.</note>For, ſuche is the wickedneſſe of the ennemyes of the truthe, that nothing canne be ſo well ſpoken, or ſo Godlye ſet foorthe, but that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12849:9"/> they be alwayes moſte readye too calumnyate and blaſpheme the ſame.</p>
               <p>As for an example: oure bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Philalethes, that the profyt of our laſte talke and communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that we haue had touchinge predeſtination, the diuine proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, and of free wyll, mighte come to manye, did cauſe it to be publiſhed, and ſet foorthe in prynte. But, Lorde God, how is he rayled agaynſt? How is his Godlye trauaile and labour taken of the moſte ſorte of men?</p>
               <p>And yet in it, all thynges are made ſo playne, that the ſimpleſt manne in the worlde, maye haue edifyinge by it:</p>
               <p>And all the obiections, that coulde be made, ſo pighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, bothe by the ſcryptures, and alſo by the authorytyes of the auncyente fathers, aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that anye reſonable manne,
<pb facs="tcp:12849:10"/> woulde holde him ſelfe ſatiſfied.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>Who be they, think ye,<note place="margin">Who thei be that ſtorme at the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note> brother Eutrapelus, that thus ſo vngodlye ſtorme agaynſte this moſt coumfortable doctrin of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination and of the diuine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God? Euen a ſort of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſtes and ſwinyſhe Epicures, whoſe gruntinge, we oughte not to regarde, or to care for. How be it,<note place="margin">Atheiſtes are in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</note> I do not doubte, but that there be many that now ſpeake euyl of the doctrine, which if they had red the booke throughoute with ſober iudgement, and with a ſingle eie, woulde lyke it well ynoughe, yea, and receiue vnſpeakable coumfort by it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>I knewe rightwel, when I toke the matter in hande, that I ſhoulde ſtyrre vp many enemies againſte me. But ſhould I therfore, haue kepte cloſe and hidden from the faithfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation that thinge, whiche the holy ghoſt wyll haue to be reueled
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12849:10"/> to al his electe and choſen people? God forfende, that for feare of the dyſpleaſure of men,<note place="margin">We ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght not for feare of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of men hyde the truthe.</note> or of the hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked worlde, we ſhould counceale or hyde anye truthe. Ye ſhal ſee, that thei wil no leſſe rage at this doctrine of the iuſtification of faith, when they ſhal heare that God without anye workes or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits going before, doeth frely iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye vs, through faith onelye in his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, our lorde &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour then they do at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of predeſtinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wil thei not by &amp; by crye out and ſay: that by thys doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, al maner of good works are cleane taken awaye, and quite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowen? For, who being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that faith onely iuſtifieth, wil geue him ſelf to do good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, or to leade a Godlye lyfe and Chriſtianlike conuerſation? But yet we muſte not becauſe of theſe blaſphemies of the wicked enemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the truthe, leaue of therfore, to teache and ſet foorth the truthe
<pb facs="tcp:12849:11"/> of this doctrine,<note place="margin">What ſcope or marke we ought too ſhut at, in ſettinge foorth the doctrin of the iuſtify<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cation of fayth.</note> that the holle glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye of oure ſaluation, in deſpight of the deuyll and of all hys Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, maye onelye and ſolelye be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the merits of the death, paſſyon and bloudeſheddynge of the onely begotten ſonne of God, our ſauioure Ieſu Chriſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>Therfore, brother Philalethes, that we maye ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what the better be edifyed in thys matter, and alſo edifye other, we doe mooſte earneſtlye deſire you, that ye wyl (ſith that we are now at leaſure, and haue nothinge els to do) ſet foorth at large this holle doctrine of iuſtification. For, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye are yet verye blinde and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunte in it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, ye ſhal finde many, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among the learned pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes, that dare boldely ſaye, that this phraſe or maner of ſpeaking. <hi>Sola fides iuſtificat:</hi> Faith only iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, is but newly inuented of the hereſykes of oure time, and that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12849:11"/> none of all the aunciente wryters of the primitiue church did euer vſe it, eyther in theyr ſermons or wrytinges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPELVS.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, is a kingdom of lyes.</note>Thys is not the fyrſt lye, that they haue made. But as their kingdome, is a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of lyes, ſo with lyes, do they laboure and ſtudye, for to mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>And that, I truſt, ſhall well appeare, or euer we haue made an end of this oure talke and communication. For, I wyll aleadge ſo manye autoriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and places oute of the auney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente wryters of the primytyue churche, wher they do plainlye af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrme wyth vs, that fayth onlye doth iuſtify, that al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo ſimple, ſhal eaſely perceaue how ſhamefully they haue belied vs &amp; oure doctrine &amp; that of a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious mind, they haue moſt trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terouſly hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the truth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaith ful congregation of gods people.
<pb facs="tcp:12849:12"/> But or euer we go any farther, I thinke it beſt too declare in what ſignification this woorde to iuſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye, oughte to be taken. As far as we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> learn this word:<note place="margin">whence this word iuſticare, to iuſtify, hath bene borowed and what it ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note> iuſtificare to iuſtify, hathe bene of the bleſſed Apoſtle ſainte Paule borowed of the common vſe of the lawe. For, in iudgement, to iuſtifye a man, it is too aſſoyle or quyte him of the crime, that is layed to his charge, or that he is accuſed of, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce him righteous, iuſt, inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cente, and giltleſſe. After the ſame maner, when we ſaye, that God doeth iuſtifye vs, our meaning is that God doth aſſoile and quite vs of al the crimes, offences and treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be laid to our charge or that we can be accuſed of, and that he doethe pronounce vs iuſte and righteous in his ſighte. That is to ſaye: That firſt he doeth par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and forgeue vs our ſinnes, he couerethe them, and doethe in no wiſe impute the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puteth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12849:12"/> vnto vs righteouſneſſe, not oure owne, which is none at all, but the righteouſneſſe of his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne Ieſu Chriſt, and ſo through, or by imputinge vnto vs the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of hys onely begotten ſonne, he doth both ſaue vs and make vs bleſſed. So doeth the holy Apoſtle expound this our iuſtification, ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing: As Dauid doeth ſet foorth the bleſſedfulnes of the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God imputethe righteouſneſſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out works, where he ſaith: bleſſed are thoſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ro.</hi> 4.</note> whoſe iniquities are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuen, whoſe ſinnes are couered-Bleſſed is the man vntoo whome the Lord imputeth no ſinne.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPELVS.</speaker>
               <p>By theſe fewe wordes that ye haue now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged, anye man maye eaſelye learne,<note place="margin">wherin our iuſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſte.</note> that our iuſtification conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in the forgeueneſſe of ſinnes and imputation of the righteouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt. Wherby the vayne and founde opinion of thoſe, that wil haue vs to be iuſtified by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes
<pb facs="tcp:12849:13"/> is cleane ouerthrowen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>I wold ſayn, that our brother Philalethes, ſhoulde briefelye declare vnto vs,<note place="margin">What it is to be iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtified by workes.</note> what it is to be iuſtifyed by workes, and agayne what it is too be iuſtifyed by fayth. For, theſe thinges, being well and ſubſtantially vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, I do not doubt, but that the teſte wyll bee a greate deale the playner.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>To be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by workes, is by our owne deedes, to deſerue remiſſion and forgeueneſſe, of ſynnes, and too pourchaſe vnto oure ſelues ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Or elles thus: They are iuſtifyed by workes, in whoſe life, there is founde ſuche cleanelineſſe and holyneſſe, as maye deſerue the teſtimonye of righteouſneſſe before the iudgement ſeat of God, or that wyth the vprighteneſſe of theyr woorkes be able to aunſwer and ſatyſfye Goddes iuſtyce and iudgemente.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:12849:13"/>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>I beleue that they are very thynne ſowen, that with the vprightneſſe of theyr workes be able to aunſwer and ſatiſfy the iuſtice and iudgemente of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>They are very thyn ſowen in dede. For non (Chriſt onely excepted) could euer do it. And therefore,<note place="margin">Chriſt on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly hath ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſfied the iuſtyce of God.</note> all the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Adam, beinge at defiaunce with their owne righteouſneſſe, oughte to crye oute wyth Dauid, and ſai: Enter not in to iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, o lord,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.</note> for in thy ſight ſhal no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g be iuſtified.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBI.</speaker>
               <p>And what is it to be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by fayth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>They are iuſtifyed by faith,<note place="margin">What it is to be iuſtyfied by fayth.</note> that being excluded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſeneſſe of workes, do by faythe take holde one the righteouſeneſſe of Chriſte, wherwyth when they are clothed and appareylled, they appeare in the ſyghte of God, not as ſynners, but as ryghteouſe perſonnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:12849:14"/>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiecti∣on. </seg>i.</label> This, me thinke, is a verye coumfortable doctrine. But yet, it wyll not be alowed of all men, for, the moſt parte wyll ſtil maintaine, that we are iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by workes and not by faith on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, aleadginge, for the probati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this their ſayinge, the ſecond chapiter of Iames,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.</note> wher he ſaieth on this maner: was not our father Abraham iuſtified throughe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, when he offered Iſaac his ſon vpon the altar? And a little after: ye ſe then, how that of woorkes a man is iuſtified, and not of faithe onlye. Either ye muſte (ſaye they) make the holy Apoſtels to diſagree or ye muſte graunte with Iames that of works man is iuſtified and not of faith onlye. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>God wotte, this is a poore helpe, that they doe bringe for them ſelues. For firſte and formoſte, let vs marke the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, that Iames doeth make me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of, and we ſhal ſoone perceiue
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12849:14"/> how ignorauntly they behaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues in expoundinge the wordes of the Apoſtell. We reade in the xv. chapiter of Geneſis,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.</note> that Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham beleued the Lord, and it was coumpted vnto him for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Which texte is of Paule a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged after this ſort: If Abraham were iuſtified by workes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.</note> he hath wherein to reioyce or glorye, but not with God. For what ſaith the ſcripture: Abraham beleued God, and it was imputed vnto him for righteouſneſſe? Wherby the holye Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Abraham was iuſty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fied .xxx. yeares afore he offered his ſonne Iſaac.</note> doeth proue moſt ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, that Abraham our father was iuſtified by faithe. But this, that Iames doeth ſpeake of, whiche is the offerynge of Iſaac, was done xxx. yeares after, that the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res did pronounce Abraham to be iuſtified, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his faith was coum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted vnto him for righteouſneſſe. Verely, fyth that .xv. yeares afore that Iſaac was borne,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gene.</hi> 22.</note> Abrahams faythe was imputed vnto hym for
<pb facs="tcp:12849:15"/> righteouſneſſe, it was impoſſible, that he ſhoulde be iuſtifyed by the offering of hys ſonne Iſaac, which was as I ſayd before .xxx. years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. What if we ſaye then, that the apoſtle doeth only go about to ſhewe,<note place="margin">What faith A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham was iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by.</note> that the fayth, whiche A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham was iuſtifyed by, was no idel or dead fayth but ſuch a faith, as made hym obedient vnto God, as it is more playnelye ſet foorthe in the .ii. to the Hebrewes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EV.</speaker>
               <p>This that ye haue brought in now, is of greate ſtrength. And truly, I do not ſee, which way thei can wind the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> briers if the hiſtory &amp; the circumſtaunces of the ſame be weyghed a ryghte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>We wil yet go to worke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them another way: and ſhew how that ther is no repugnaunce at al in the doctrine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtels. For, what contrariety or repugnaunce could ther be in their doctrine, ſith that they wer both lead by one ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rit? Therfore, we ſhal marke, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12849:15"/> the holy Apoſtle. S. Paul in his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtels to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romains &amp; to the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lathians, did diſpute and reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that did atribute iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to workes, but.<note place="margin">Note this dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly.</note> S Iames did wryte againſt them, which did vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly contempne and deſpiſe good workes. And therfore Paule ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the cauſes of our iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iames the effectes &amp; frutes of the ſame. Paul declareth how we are iuſtifyed: Iames how we are kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be iuſtified. Paul excludeth workes, as not the cauſe of our iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Iames approueth wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes as effects proceding of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Paul denieth that any good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be not iuſtyfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Iames affirmeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they which be iuſtified ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in no wiſe be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out good woorkes. But ye ſhall heare what. S Auguſtine hath left vnto vs, by writing, touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter:<note place="margin">Augu. <hi>83.</hi> questionum questi. <hi>76.</hi> Gloſſa or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaria.</note> 
                  <hi>Quod Abraham per fidem ſine operibus iuſtificatus eſt, de operibus qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e precede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, intelligitur, quia per opera quae fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, iuſtus non ſuit, ſed ſola fide.
<pb facs="tcp:12849:16"/> Hic de operibus agitur, quae fidem ſequn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.</note> 
                  <hi>per quae amplius iuſtificabatur, cum tam per fidem fuiſſet iuſtus. Vnde Paulus dicit: Fide obtulit Abraham Iſaac, quum tentaretur. Haec oblatio eſt opus et te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonium fidei et iuſtitiae.</hi> That is too ſaye: That Abraham was iuſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by faith without works, it is to be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of the workes that dyd goo before: For, he was not righteouſe throughe the workes, which he had done, but by faythe only. Here it is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the works that folowe the faith, whereby he was more iuſtifyed, whereas he was alreadye before made righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe by faithe. Therfore, Paule ſayeth:<note place="margin">The offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe of Iſaac is a teſtimony of the fayth &amp; righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe of A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braham.</note> Abraham did offer Iſaac with faith, when he was tempted. This offeringe is a worke and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonye of his faythe and of hys righteouſneſſe. Theſe things, did he write vpon Iames epiſtell. If the offering of Iſaac, is a teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the faith and righteouſneſſe of Abraham: He coulde not be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyfied
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12849:16"/> by it, but rather it was therby declared that he was iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed alreadye. So that this obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.</note> which he ſhewed vnto the word of the Lord, did only ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt and ſhew, that he was when he beleued Gods promiſes, made ryghteous before God, throughe the ſame fayth and beleue, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyth he was ſo ſtrengthened, that geuynge the glorye vnto God, he perſwaded him ſelfe fullye, that he which had promiſed, was alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do the thynge, that he hadde promyſed thoughe it ſemed neuer ſo ſtraunge, nor ſo muche againſt the common courſe of nature. And therefore the Apoſtle concludethe ryghte well, that it was imputed vnto him for ryghteouſneſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPELVS.</speaker>
               <p>As far as I do remember, I haue hearde you tell, that otherwhyles, to be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifyed, is to be declared righteous and iuſte. As when the prophette Dauid ſayeth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.</note> That thou mayeſt
<pb facs="tcp:12849:17"/> be iuſtified in thy wordes &amp; ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, when thou art-iudged, that is to ſaye: that thou mayeſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared iuſte, and thy goodneſſe and trueth appeare, in performing thy promiſes, when man eyther of cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rioſite, or of arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie wold iudge thy workes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>This is wel reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred. And therefore, this ſhall we note by the waye,<note place="margin">This worde to iuſtifye is other wiſe take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Paule then of Iames.</note> that this worde to iuſtifie, is not taken of Paul in that ſignification, that ſaincte Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes doeth take it in. For, of Paul it is taken for to deliuer from ſyn, and for to impute righteouſneſſe: but Iames doeth take it, for to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare one iuſte and righteous. Agayne Paul ſpeaketh of a liuely faythe, whiche can no more be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good workes,<note place="margin">Fayth is not taken of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtels in one ſigny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fication.</note> than the Sunne can be without light, or fyer with out heate: But Iames ſpeaketh of an idell and deadde faythe, whiche maye be in the reprobate, yea, in the diuell hym ſelf, as the Apoſtell
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12849:17"/> writteth in theſame place. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, whether ought one texte too geue place to many: or manye too geue place to one?<note place="margin">One text muſt geue place to manye.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDI.</speaker>
               <p>It ſtandeth with reaſon that one texte ſhoulde rather geue place too manye, than that manye ſhould geue place to one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALE.</speaker>
               <p>For, this one text of Iames, that ſemeth to attribute iuſtifycation vntoo workes, how manye notable textes and ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſhal ye fynde in the other Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall ſcriptures, that teach the contrarye?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>And we do all pray you, brother Philalethes, that ye will aleadge the chiefeſt and moſt principall of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For as touching that place, which thei do aleadge &amp; bring out of the ſecond chapiter of Iames, ye haue well ſatiſfied my mind, I thanke god therfore.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>That wil I gladli do: yea I wil be ſides this ioigne vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> autorities of the ſcriptures &amp; word of God, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12849:18"/> ſayinges of the aunciaunt fathers of the primitiue churche, that ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemies of the trueth, whiche doe moſte lyengly blowe abrode, that we haue no ſuche ſtuffe, maye at length, ſeing our greate rycheſſe, vtterly be ſhamed and confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>Forſothe in ſo doinge, ye ſhal do vs all a greate pleaſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>I might here bring many notable ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces out of the olde and new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, wherein the excellencye of faith is highly ſetfoorth, but I wil at this preſent omitte or leaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and aledge only thoſe places, that do moſt chiefly perteyne to iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 13.</note>Firſte in the Actes of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, we haue theſe wordes writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that Paul made vnto the Iewes that were at An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochia, a cytte of Piſidia: Be it knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto you therfore, brethern that through this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is preached
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12849:18"/> vnto you the forgeueneſſe of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And that from all thinges, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche ye coulde not be iuſtified by the law of Moſes, by hym eueri one that beleueth, is iuſtified. Theſe wordes are ſo playne, that they nede no expoſition at al. For, all men, oneleſſe they will be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully blynde ſtyll, maye eaſely ſee, that he taketh awaye altogether iuſtification from the lawe of Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes,<note place="margin">Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye all together from the lawe of Moſes &amp; atributed vnto faith</note> and doeth attribute it vntoo fayth in our ſauiour Ieſu Chriſte. But in the Epiſtel to the Romai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s the holy apoſtell maketh the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter more playne, where he ſayeth: They haue all ſynned, and are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted or voyde of the glorie of God. But they are iuſtified freely by his grace, through the redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that is in Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.</note> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God hath ſetfoorthe too be a pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſſer of mercy, through fayth in his bloude.</p>
               <p>Let theſe wordes be diligentely conſidered and weyghed, and then
<pb facs="tcp:12849:19"/> I do not doubt, but that they, that be of an indifferente iudgemente, wyl ſone agree vnto our doctrine. Firſt, the Apoſtle ſayeth, that they haue all ſynned, and that they are depriued of the glorye of God. By whiche wordes he doth moſt liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye put before oure eyes the myſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable eſtate, that whole mankind was in. Secondly he doth effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlye ſhewe, how and by what meanes we are deliuered from it, I meane:<note place="margin">What be the meanes wherby we are iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtified, or deliuered from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of dampna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> frome that dampnable eſtate, that we are in by our owne nature, and fyrſt byrthe, when he ſayeth: But they are iuſtifyed fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye by his grace. Nowe, if we be iuſtified frely by the grace of God, wher are our works, merits or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruings become? For if any wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, deſeruinges or merits, do go before oure iuſtification, how can it be ſayed, that we are iuſtifyed freelye by the grace of God oure heauenlye father?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12849:19"/>
               <speaker>EVTRAPELVS.</speaker>
               <p>In deede it might rather be ſaied, that we are iuſtified in reſpecte of oure owne workes and merites. And ſo the ſayinge of the Apoſtell coulde not ſtande, where he ſayth in an other place: By grace ye are ſaued tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe fayth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epho.</hi> 2.</note> and that not of youre ſelues: it is the gyft of God, not of workes, leaſte anye man ſhoulde boaſte him ſelfe. Whereunto the ſayinge of a moſte aunciente wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſemeth wel to agree: His wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des are theſe:<note place="margin">Ambroſius de vocatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne gentium li. <hi>1.</hi> capi. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sicut nulla ſunt tam deteſtanda faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora, quae poſſunt gratiae arcere donum, ita nulla poſſunt tam proeclara opera ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtere, quibus hoc quod gratis tribuitur, perretributionis iudicium debeatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vileſceret, enim, redemptio ſanguinis Chriſti, ac miſerecordia del humanorum operum praerogatiuae ſuccumberet, ſi iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtificatio quae f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t pergratiam praeceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus meritis deberetur, vt non mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus largientis, ſed merces eſſet operan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12849:20"/>
               <p>That is to ſaye: As there be no ſynnes ſo deteſtable, that can kepe of, the gyft of grace, ſo there can be no workes ſo excellente, that vnto them, by the iudgement of retribu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion or recompence, the ſame ſhuld be due, which is freely geuen and graunted. For, the redemption of the bloud of Chriſte ſhoulde waxe vyle, and the mercye of God, be fayne to geue place to the preroga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiue of mens works, if iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is don or wrought by grace were due vnto the merits that go before, ſo that it ſhoulde not be the free gyfte of the gyuer, but the rewarde or hyre of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. What other thinge, I beſech you, doeth this holy father meane but that we are without any me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, goynge before, iuſtified frely by the mere goodneſſe and grace of God,<note place="margin">To attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute iuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fication vnto any merites going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, is a derogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the grace of God.</note> through faith in the bloud of his ſonne Ieſu Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Yea, he doeth playnely affirme that it is a derogation of the grace
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12849:20"/> of God, and of the merites of the death, paſſion and bloudſhedding<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of his ſonne Ieſu Chriſt, to attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute our iuſtification vnto any me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rites, goynge before, and alſo that it is to conſtrayne the glorie of the free mercy of God to yelde or geue place vnto the dignitie and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of mens workes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>This is a verye godly ſayinge and moſt worthy to be noted of all men. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>2</label> But yet in the meane whyle they will ſaye ſtyll, that although we fynde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that fayth iuſtifieth, yet we fynde not: <hi>quod ſola fides iuſtificat,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">ſolifidians.</note> that fayth onely iuſtifieth, ſo that this worde onely, or alone hath be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> newly added by heretykes, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> whom they do commonly calle Solifidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.<note place="margin">Although we haue not in the ſcripturs this word ſola, only or alone yet haue we many wordes that be of like force.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>Will ye that I tell you the truethe, neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Dydimus? Theſe ſtout cham<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pions of Antychriſte, doe nothinge els but ſeke a knot in a ruſſhe, as
<pb facs="tcp:12849:21"/> the common laiyne prouerbe is, For, al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>houghe we haue not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſelye this worde, ſola, onelye or alone, yet haue we many other wordes, that are equipollente, or equiualente, that is, of the ſame importaunce &amp; force. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy ghoſt ſaith: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are iuſtified freli by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of god through the rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption, which is in Chriſt Ieſu whome God hathe ſetfoorth to be a purchaſſer of mercye, throughe faythe in his bloude: doeth he not exclude all maner of works deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinges or merits from our iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, attributinge it vnto fayth onelye wherby we do apprehende and take holde on the grace and mercye of God, ſo ſurely ſealed vp vnto vs with the bloud of that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculate and vnſpotted lamb, our ſauiour Ieſu Chriſt?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.</note> In the ſame ſelfe chapiter he ſayth agayne: we conclude that a man is iuſtified by fayth withoute the workes of the lawe. Who doeth not ſee, that he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12849:21"/> doth here alſo put away all maner of thynges from our iuſtification, fayth onelye excepted?<note place="margin">What Paul vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> works of the lawe.</note> I am ſure that by the workes of the lawe, he vnderſtandethe thoſe workes that God doethe requyre of vs in hys word, and whether ye wyll refer them to the ceremonies, or to the morall preceptes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, that be conteined in the ſame, it is all one thing to me. For the holye ghoſt doeth teſtifye euery where that the works of the lawe do not iuſtify. Of the ceremonies, rites, &amp; ſacrifices, we haue this ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient teſtimony of the prophette Dauid: Thou deſireſt no ſacrifice,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>pſal.</hi> 51,</note> thoughe I wold geue it: thou deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt not in burnte offeringe. And therfore being ſore troubled in his conſcience, for his hainous offence that he had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, he did caſte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eies of his faith vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bloud and merit of the ſauior promiſed, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: waſhe me throughly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mine iniquity &amp; clenſe me from my ſyn.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>pſal.</hi> 51.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12849:22"/> Purge me with Yſope &amp; I ſhalbe cleane: waſſhe me, and I ſhalbe whyter then ſnowe. Deliuer me from bloud, o God, whiche art the God of my ſaluation. And frome thence ſainct Paul ſemeth to haue borowed this his ſayinge:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.</note> The bloud of Bulles and Goates cann not take awaye ſynnes.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gala.</hi> 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And as for the workes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the morall preceptes &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deu.</hi> 28.</note> we are ſure that they canne not iuſtifie.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Abac.</hi> 1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.</note> For why? who is able to do them with ſuche a perfection as God doth requyre? And therfore heare what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtel ſayeth in his Epiſtel to the Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gala.</hi> 2.</note> As many as are of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the lawe, are vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> curſe. For, it is written: Curſed is eueri man that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinueth not in al thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that are written in the booke of the lawe, for to do theym. And that no man is iuſtified by the law in the ſight of God, it is euident. For, the iuſte ſhall lyue by faythe.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12849:22"/> Againe in the ſame ſelfe Epiſtell thus doth the apoſtel write: know that a man is not iuſtified by the workes of the lawe, but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith of Ieſu Chriſte, and euen we haue beleued in Ieſus Chriſte, that we mighte be iuſtified by the fayth of Chriſte, and not by the workes of the lawe. Becauſe that by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the lawe no fleſhe can be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified.</p>
               <p>All theſe ſayinges do ſufficiently declare, that althoughe, as I ſayed before, we haue not expreſſely this worde, ſola, onely or alon, yet we haue many other wordes that are of like importaunce, and force.<note place="margin">The ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the truth are to be likened vnto the Arians.</note> So that in this point, we maye likene the enemies of the trueth vnto the wicked Arians, whiche becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe words, homouſios &amp; conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantialis, be not founde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures, will in no wiſe admit nor alowe them, although the thinges ſignified by them, are moſte infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly and certaynly conteyned and
<pb facs="tcp:12849:23"/> ſette oute in the booke of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPELVS.</speaker>
               <p>There com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth nowe in to my mynde a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſaying of the Apoſtle, which as I do ſuppoſe, wyl ſerue wel for oure purpoſe. In the Epiſtle to the Philyppians,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phi.</hi> 3.</note> he wryteth on this maner: The things that wer vantage vnto me, the ſame I cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted loſſe for Chriſtes ſake, and do iudge them to be dounge, that I might wynne Chriſt, and mighte be founde in him, that is: not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge myne owne righteouſneſſe, whyche is of the lawe, but that, whiche is throughe the fayeth of Chriſte, euen the righteouſneſſe, which is of God through fayth.<note place="margin">What they muſt do that wil enioy the righte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of Chriſt.</note> It is euydente and playne that ſaynt Paule here in this place, makethe a compariſon betwixt things that are contrary, ſhewinge that they, which will obtayne or enioye the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt muſte vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly forſake their own. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the Epiſtle to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</note> he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12849:23"/> doeth playnelye affyrme, that the cauſe of the ruyne and fall of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wes, was becauſe that thei went a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bout to eſtabliſh their own righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and wold in no wiſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them ſelues to the righteouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God. Wherunto, to make the matter the more plain, he doth by &amp; bi ad theſe words For Chriſt is the end of the law for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o euerye one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beleueth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDI.</speaker>
               <p>I do not very well vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande this laſte ſentence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EV.</speaker>
               <p>The meaninge of it is this: The end of the lawe is to iuſtlye them, that do obſerue it. But who dyd euer obſerue it? Therefore,<note place="margin">i. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note> Chriſt hauing fulfilled it for vs, is through faith, made vnto vs of god wiſedom, righteouſneſſe, holineſſe and redemption. So that what ſo euer is lacking or wanting in vs, it is by his perfect obedience, moſt aboundantlye ſupplyed, as farre foorthe as we haue felloweſhyppe wyth hym, throughe fayth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:12849:24"/>
               <speaker>ALBION</speaker>
               <p>It reioiceth my very heart to heare ſuche coumfortable ſentences out of the ſcriptures and worde of God. But I wolde fayne learn, whether the old doctors doe holde with vs, that fayethe onely doeth iuſtifie. For, that is one of the thinges, which the enemies do ſtoutely denye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>Er I do ſatiſfye your deſire, I doe intende to aledge yet two or three golden ſentences out of the Apoſtel: which canne not well be omitted in thys caſe.</p>
               <p>The firſte ſhall ye haue in the Epiſtel to Titus,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Titu.</hi> 3.</note> where he writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on this wyſe: Not by the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of righteouſnes, which we had done, but according to his mercye he ſaued vs, that we beinge iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by his grace ſhoulde be made heyrs, accordinge too the hope of eternall lyfe.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is muche like vntoo this, and is ſetfoorth in the ſecond
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12849:24"/> Epiſtell to Timothee, after thys maner: God hathe ſaued vs,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Timo.</hi> 1.</note> and called vs with an holye callinge, not accordinge to our workes,<note place="margin">The pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of God doth exclude al merites and deſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uings fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cation of man.</note> but according to his own purpoſe and grace, whiche was geuen vnto vs throughe Chriſt Ieſus, afore the worlde was. Truely, wherſoeuer this purpoſe of God is, there wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, merits, or deſeruinges, can take no place in the iuſtification or ſaluation of man. Wherby, it muſt nedes folowe (as we can ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther none other of the ſentences nowe aleadged) that by the free mercy and goodneſſe of God, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and taken hold vpon by fayth, we are deliuered from oure ſynnes and from euerlaſting dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and made felowe heyers with his ſonne Ieſu Chriſt whoſe righteouſneſſe he doth impute vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, of his eternall and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge kingdome of heauen. All theſe thinges, I ſay, do we obtain, throughe fayeth onely, withoute
<pb facs="tcp:12849:25"/> anye merites goynge before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>Say what ye wil, the enemies do ſtyll whiſper in to the eares of the ſymple and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt perſons, that this is, but a newe ſounde doctrine, and that none of all the auncient doctours did euer teache it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>Ye myght haue learned that thys is playne fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in the autority, that we haue already broughte out of ſaint Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,<note place="margin">Aug. 83. que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtionu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtione<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 76, Gloſſa ordi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naria.</note> whoſe wordes are theſe: <hi>Quod Abraham per fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſine operibus iuſtificatus eſt, de operibus quae prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedebant, intelligitur, quia per opera, quae fecit, iustus non fuit ſed ſola fide.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whiche we haue alreadye en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhed thus: That Abraham was iuſtified by faith without workes, it is to be vnderſtanded of the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes, that dyd go before. For, he was not ryghteous throughe the workes, whyche he had done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>ſed ſola fide,</hi> but by faieth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye. If it be an hereſye to ſaye that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12849:25"/> faythe onely doeth iuſtifye, let me ſee, how they can excuſe Saynte Auguſtine of hereſye. Vnto hym, maye we ioygne father Ambroſe, who wrytinge vppon the epiſtell to the Romayns,<note place="margin">Amb. in epi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſto. ad Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manos ca. 4.</note> ſpeaketh on this manner:
<q>Iuſtificari ſunt gratis, quia nihil operantes neque vicem reddentes ſola fide iuſtificati ſunt dono dei.</q>
               </p>
               <p>That is to ſaye: They were iuſtyfied freelye, for, they worc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge nothinge, nor makinge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye recompence, they were iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed throughe faythe onelye, by the gyfte of God. Agayne, in the ſame place, theſe be hys wordes:
<q>Sic decretum dicit a deo, vt ceſſante lege,<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> ſolam fidem gratia dei poſcere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ad ſalutem.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Whyche maye be englyſhed thus: He ſayethe, that it was ſo decreed of God, that the lawe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge at an ende, the grace of God ſhoulde requyre faythe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, or faythe onelye vnto ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12849:26"/>
               <p>Theſe be alſo his wordes:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hoc ipſum munit exemplo prophetae. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atitudinem hominis di it, cui deus accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam fert iuſtitiam ſine operibus. Beatos dicit quibus hoc ſanxit deus, vt ſine labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re et aliqua obſeruatione, ſola fide iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficentur apud deum.</hi> That is to ſay: he doeth ſtrengthene or fenſe this by the example of the prophette. He ſaith that the ſame man hath bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedfulnes or that bleſſedfulnes per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tained and belongeth to that man, vnto whom God imputeth righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe withoute workes, he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them bleſſed vnto whom God had made this decree, that wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute laboure, and withoute anye obſeruation, they ſhoulde, by faith onely be iuſtified before God. And in an other place:<note place="margin">Idem in. <hi>9.</hi> ca. ciuſdem epistol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</note> 
                  <hi>Sola fides ad ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem poſita eſt.</hi> Faythe onelye, ſayeth he, is appoynted vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. Ye maye ſee nowe, howe many tymes, this olde father doth vſe this worde, <hi>ſola,</hi> alone or only, which the aduerſaries or enemies
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12849:26"/> doe accuſe of hereſye. But let vs heare what the other auncient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do ſay concerning this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe are Ieroms words vpon the Epiſtle to the Romains.<note place="margin">Ieronimus in 10. caput epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto. ad Ro.</note>
               </p>
               <q>Ignorantes quod ſola fide iuſtificat de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, et ſe ex operibus legis, quam numqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cuſtodierunt iuſtos eſſe putantes, nolue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt ſe ſubijcere remiſſioni peccatorum, ne peccatores fuiſſe viderentur.</q>
               <p>That is to ſaye: They not kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winge that God iuſtifieth by faith onely, and ſuppoſing them ſelues to be iuſt by the works of the law, whiche they neuer obſerued, they would not ſubmit them ſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the remiſſion of ſynnes, leaſte they ſhoulde ſeeme too haue bene ſynners.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPELVS.</speaker>
               <p>By this au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritye, that ye haue aleadged oute of Ierome, two thinges maye be learned. Firſte and foremoſt we learne that God doeth iuſtifye by fayth only, which, of the enemies is coumpted playn hereſye, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon
<pb facs="tcp:12849:27"/> we maye conclude that they be wrapped in the ſame moſte pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiferous ignoraunce that the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes and Phariſees were wrapped in,<note place="margin">What cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dit ought to be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto the enemi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es of the truth and what ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce they be wrapped in.</note> and that therfore no credit ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght to be geuen vnto them, nor yet to their doctrine. For why? thei be altogether ignoraunt in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſte principall poynte of our religion: cauſinge the people to ſeeke for ſaluation, wher there is nothinge elles but deſperation and ſhippewracke of conſcyence. Secondlye, we ſee here moſte e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidentlye the cauſe whye the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes and Phariſees,<note place="margin">Why the ſcribes &amp; Phariſes wer vtter enemies vnto the goſpell. Luc. 18.</note> were ſuche extreme enemies vnto the goſpel, which offereth vnto all them that wyll beleue in oure ſauioure Ieſu Chriſt, free pardone and remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their ſinnes. Forſoth, they iuſtyfyed them ſelues that they were perfect and withoute ſynne. Leſt then they ſhuld loſe any part of their eſtimation (for thei, ſought their owne glorye more than the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12849:27"/> glorye of God) they woulde in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe ſubmitte them ſelues vnto the doctryne of the remyſſion of ſinnes, nor yet receaue the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall pardone, that was offered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them of God. For, then they muſte needes, to haue acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged them ſelues with the other to haue bene ſinners. But they would none of that, beinge in this pointe moſte like vnto oure greate Rabbis,<note place="margin">Why our great rab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bis will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge their errour.</note> whiche althoughe their conſcyences beare them recorde, that they be in a moſte pernicious errour, and haue moſt ſhamefully deceiued the people, yet becauſe they wyll not myniſhe one iote of their reputation, that they haue hadde amonge ſimple and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunte peſonnes, they haue lye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffer too continue and remaine in their erroure, and to be ſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blynge blockes ſtyll vnto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, than ones too reuoke theyr erroure, and to geue the glorye vnto God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:12849:28"/>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>And ſuppoſe ye, that thys is the cauſe of their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacye?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>It appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that is ſo, elles wold they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke or recant their erroure, and as oure brother Eutrapelus ſayd, geue the glorye vnto God. But we wyll leaue them vntoo theyr iudge, who at length wyll, by his righteous iudgemente,<note place="margin">God ſend him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes.</note> ſend a Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hu, who ſhal make hauok of them all: and ſo proceade to the reſte of oure matter. Hylarius in the .ix. Canon vpon Mathewe,<note place="margin">Hilarius cano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne nono in Math.</note> and vpon theſe words: <hi>Remittuntur tibi peccata tua.</hi> Thy ſynnes are forgeuen the: writeth on this maner.</p>
               <q>Mouet ſcribas, remiſſum ab honine peccatum. Hominem enim tantum, in Chiriſto Ieſu contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ebantur, et remiſſum ab eo, quod lex laxare non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erat. Fides enim ſola iuſtificat.</q>
               <p>That is to wytte: It moueth the ſcribes, that ſynne was forgeuen by man. For they did only behold man in Chriſt Ieſu, and that to be forgeuen of him, whiche the lawe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12849:28"/> could not releaſe. For fayth onely doeth iuſtifye. This texte is verye playne. For, firſt and foremoſt, he ſayeth that the ſcribes wer moued becauſe that Chriſt forgaue ſynne whome they iudged to be a nude and bare man, but ſpeciallye that he toke vppon him to forgeue and pardon that, which the law, could neyther releaſſe nor forgeue. For theſe were theyr wordes: Whye doeth this man ſpeake ſuche blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemyes? Who can forgeue ſyns but God onelye? And finallye he doeth knyt vppe the matter with theſe words: <hi>Fides enim ſola iuſtificat:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">If it be an here<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that faith only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Mat. 2</note> For, faith only doth iuſtify. If we for ſaying that fayth only doth iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifye, do deſerue to be called here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes: how ſhall, I beſeche you. S. Auguſtine, Ambroſe, Ierome and Hylarius be excuſed, which do vſe the ſame phraſe and maner of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kinge, that we do vſe, and mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne the ſame doctrine, that we do maintayn? Shall they not with
<pb facs="tcp:12849:29"/> vs be called Solifidians?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe of a truthe, I doe vnderſtande and perceaue, that I haue bene ſhamefullye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guyled by theſe bragginge mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes of the clergye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>Ye wyll ſaye ſo, by that tyme, that ye haue hearde all. I haue alreadye aleadged .iiii. of the moſt aunciente of tha latine wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: nowe wyll I ioygne vntoo them .iiii. of the greeke doctours I wyll not cumber the reader with ſo many as I coulde nowe bringe in, for, I ſuppoſe theſe fewe to be ſufficiente, for to ſatiſfye anye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable mannes mynde. Firſt we wyll brynge in,<note place="margin">Origenes in tertium caput epiſtole ad Romanos.</note> olde father O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rygene, who vppon the epiſtell to the Romaynes writeth on this manner:
<q>Apoſtolus hiſce verbis: Arbitramur igitur fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de iuſtificati hominem abſque operibus legis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit ſufficere ſolius fidei <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſtificationem, ita vt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens quis tantummodo, iuſtificetur etiam ſi nihil operis ab eo fue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it expletum. Quod ſi exemplum requiramus, quis ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e operibus ſola fide iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catus ſit, ſufficere arbitror illum latronem, qui
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12849:29"/> cum Chriſto crucifixus, clamauit ei de cruce: Domine Ieſu, memento mei, cum veneris, in regnum tuum, nec aliud quicquam deſcribitur boni operis eius, in euangelijs, ſed pro hac ſola fide, ait ei Ieſus: Amen dico tibi: Hodie mecum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris in paradiſo. Per fidem ergo iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt hic latro, abſque operibus legis. Quia ſuper hoc dominus non requiſiuit, quid prius operatus eſſet, nec expectauit, quid operis cum credidiſſet expleret, ſed ſola confeſſione iuſtificatum comitem ſibi paradiſum ingreſſurus aſſumpſit.</q>
               </p>
               <p>That is to ſaye:<note place="margin">Rom. 3.</note> Paul by theſe wordes: We ſuppoſe therefore, that manne is iuſtified by faythe with out the workes of the lawe, affyrmethe that the iuſtifycation of faythe alone or of fayeth onelye is ſufficyente, ſo that anye manne beleauinge onelye, canne be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifyed, althoughe no manner of worke hath bene fulfylled or done by hym.</p>
               <p>And if we requyre an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who was iuſtified by faythe onelye without workes,<note place="margin">Luc. 23,</note> I ſuppoſe that the ſame theefe doeth ſuffice,
<pb facs="tcp:12849:30"/> who when he was crucifyed wyth Chriſt, did crye vnto hym from the croſſe: Lord Ieſu, remember me, when thou comeſt in to thy kinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Neyther anye good other worke of hys, is deſcribed or ſette foorthe vnto vs in the goſpelles. But for thys fayeth onely, Ieſus ſayed vnto him: Verely I ſaye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the, this day thou ſhalt be with me in paradyſe. This thefe then was iuſtified by fayth without the workes of the lawe. For the Lord did not vpon this requyre, what he had wrought before, neither did he looke what worke he ſhould do after he did beleue, but beynge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye to enter in to paradiſe, he toke him for his waitinge man, beinge iuſtifyed by that confeſſion onely. Beſides this he doeth aleadge the example of the ſynnefull woman and of the Publican,<note place="margin">Luc. 7.18.</note> that be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned of in the Goſpell of Luke, whome he doeth alſo affirme, too haue bene iuſtified by fayth onely,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12849:30"/> withoute any reſpecte of workes, merites, or deſeruinges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>I am affrayed leſt ſome, hearinge this doctryne ſo <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiecti∣on. </seg>3</label> largelye ſet foorthe, doe waxe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, negligente and ſlacke in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of good workes, ſythe that fayth alone, doth ſuffyſe to iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, yea I feare alſo leaſte they geue them ſelues to lyue lycenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlye and to folow the luſtes and the concupiſcences of the fleſhe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> Origene doeth him ſelfe make aunſwer to the ſame obiection, ſayinge: If any man doeth liue wickedly after iuſtification,<note place="margin">We are not deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oure ſyns to this end that we ſhuld walowe in them agayne.</note> withoute doubte he hath deſpiſed the grace of iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Neyther doeth any receaue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion or forgeueneſſe of ſinnes to this ende, that he ſhould thinke that licence to ſynne agayn, is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto him. For, a pardone not of the ſynnes to come, but of the ſynnes paſſed is geuen or graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in iuſtification. But of thys
<pb facs="tcp:12849:31"/> we wyll ſpeake more amply here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, when we ſhall haue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon too talke of thoſe good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, that do ſpringe and proceade of the true iuſtifyinge faith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>Let vs therefore hear what the other greecke doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours do ſaye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>With a good wyll. Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſius vpon the thirde to the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lathians writeth briefli thus:<note place="margin">Athanaſius</note> 
                  <hi>Nunc pla <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e demo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>strat fidem ipſam vel ſolam iuſtificandi virtutem habere</hi> Now ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he, doth he playnly ſhewe that the ſame fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he, yea beinge alone hath power to iuſtifye. Wherunto Chriſoſtome agreeth ſayinge:
<q>
                     <note place="margin">Chriſoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus in epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolam ad Rom. Homeli. 7.</note>Hic virtute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dei oſtendit, quod non ſolum ſaluauit, ſed et iuſtificauit, nullis ad hoc vſus operibus, ſed fidem tantum exigens.</q> That is to ſay: he ſheweth the ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue and power of God, how that he did not onely ſaue,<note place="margin">Baſilius Hemeli. de humilitate.</note> but alſo iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifye vſing no workes vnto it, but requiring faith only. But among all other, this ſayinge of Baſilius
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12849:31"/> is moſt worthye to be noted:
<q>Ea demum perfecta eſt et integra gloria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio in deo, quando neque de ſua quiſqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ipſius iuſtitia ſuberbit, ſed agnoſcit. Vera deſtitutum iuſtitia ſola ſe in Chriſtum fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de iuſtificatum.</q> Which golden words maye be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſhed after thys maner: That at length, is a perfecte, and ſounde reioycinge in God, when a man doeth not bragge or boaſte of his owne ryghteouſeneſſe but doeth acknowledge, that beynge voyde of true righteouſneſſe, he is iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifyed throughe fayeth onelye in Chriſt. Many ſuche lyke thynges, are redde in the wrytinges of the aunciente fathers, whereby all menne maye ſee, that we are not the fyrſt, that haue vſed this word ſola, alone or onelye, to expreſſe the meanynge of the Apoſtell, and to ſet foorth the glory of the grace of God. For the fathers did vſe it a fore vs, whoſe writinges they doe make equall wyth the Canony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſcripture.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12849:32"/>
               <p>They ſay, that we haue it not in the words of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtel.<note place="margin">Why do they not ſo in this poynte.</note> Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tel that to the fathers, whom they do take for the pilours of the church. Let them contend &amp; ſtriue with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rather tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with vs. To be ſhort if it be an hereſy to ſay that faith on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in Chriſt doth iuſtify, thei muſt accuſe thoſe auncient fathers of he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſy, yea they muſt coumpt them to be the captayns of al heretyks.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRA.</speaker>
               <p>What ſhyfte doe they make, when they feele them ſelues preſſed with ſo manye au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torities of the olde fathers? Wyth what face, can they reiecte or caſt of thys worde, ſolam, alone or onelye?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>There be ſome, which when they can not for ſhame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe it, are wonte to flye to this ſtartinge hole:<note place="margin">The eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the enemies.</note> They graunt that we are iuſtifyed by fayth onely in Chriſt: but they adde that thys is onelye done at the begynninge of fayth, when we begynne firſte to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12849:32"/> beleue in Chriſt, and ſo they wyll haue vs to vnderſtand, this to be Paulles meaninge: that neyther ſynnes did hinder the gentilles,<note place="margin">A verye goodlye ſhift I wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raunt you</note> but that as ſone as they beganne to beleue in Chriſt, they were iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifyed by faythe onely: nor wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes farther the Iewes, when they likewiſe came to Chriſt, but vnto them alſo was faythe imputed for righteouſneſſe: And ſo at length, they doo conclude, that yf they, which be ones iuſtifyed by faythe, do after theyr iuſtification, ſinne again, they can no more be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed by fayth, that is to ſay, frely, as affore, but by workes, that is to ſaye, by ſatiſfaction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPELVS.</speaker>
               <p>After my iudgement, this is but a homelye euaſion or ſtarting hole. For, yf they take this worde, to be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, for to be deliuered from ſin: it is manyfeſte and playne, that the ſame iuſtification, that conſiſteth in the gratuite &amp; free remiſſion of
<pb facs="tcp:12849:33"/> ſinnes,<note place="margin">Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by we are deliuered from ſyn, is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ri vnto vs as longe as we liue. Math. 6. 1. Ioa. 2.</note> is neceſſary vnto vs, al our liues time, onleſſe this were vayn, which, accordinge to the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord, we do daily pray for, ſayinge: And foregeue vs our treſpaſſes as we forgeue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs, Iohn ſaied vnto them that dyd beleeue and were iuſtified, My lytle babes, if any man doeth ſinne, we haue an aduocate with the father, Ieſus Chriſte the righteouſe, and he is the ſatiſfaction for our ſynnes. He ſayeth not: he was the ſatiſfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for oure ſinnes, nowe therfore ye muſt be iuſtifified by your own workes, and make ſatiſfaction, for youre ſynnes: but he doeth ſet foorthe vnto the churche of God, the endleſſe and euerlaſting ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of Chriſte, that is to ſaye, the free remiſſion and forgeuenes of ſynnes or iuſtification, whiche we do obtayne throughe fayth in him. Or if they vnderſtande it of righteouſeneſſe, which is the effect
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12849:33"/> of this iuſtification, whereby our hartes are purged and our life re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed. Yet it can not ſo be appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto fayth, that it ſhould onlye pertayne to the beginninge of it, and all the reſt of our lyfe require the righteouſneſſe of works,<note place="margin">Similitude</note> wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by we ſhoulde be ſaued. For, that were, as if a man ſhould ſaye, that the ſoule doeth onely quickene the body at the beginninge, but not ſo afterwardes: as thoughe all the quickening or viuifying, ſhuld not come of the ſoule alone, but of the operations of the bodye.<note place="margin">Abac. 1. Rom. 1. Gala. 3.</note> The righteouſe, ſayeth the Apoſtell, liueth by fayth. I do not denye, but that the lyfe of the righteouſe is adorned and beutyfyed wyth manye vertues, but yet it canne be attributed too none of them, but too fayethe onelye, that oure heartes beynge clenſed, wee lyue godlye in the ſighte of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>I hearde ones cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiecti∣on. </seg>4</label> gentyll men of my cleargye
<pb facs="tcp:12849:34"/> reaſon after this ſorte: If to be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyfied, is to be delyuered frome ſynne: Fayth onely doeth not iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifye, but loue alſo. And for the probation of theyr ſayinge, they bringe theſe words of Chriſt:<note place="margin">Luc. 7.</note> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye ſinnes are forgeuen her, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that ſhe loued muche. Lo, ſaye they, here remiſſion of ſinnes, is playnlye attributed vnto loue. Agayn: are not theſe Peters wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.</note> Loue couereth the multitude of ſinnes? Who doeth not ſee now ſaye they, that loue doeth aſwell iuſtifye as faith?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALE.</speaker>
               <p>I aunſwer that the loue of this woman, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> was not the cauſe of hyr iuſtifycation or forgeueneſſe of ſynnes, but a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the ſame. She hadde obtained throughe fayth in Chriſt remiſſion of ſynnes, whereby ſhe beinge iuſtified, did loue him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceadynglye, and did openlye ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe that loue.</p>
               <p>That it is ſo, it maye be proued
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12849:34"/> eaſelye by the woordes of oure ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uioure Ieſu Chriſte, whiche he ſpake vnto her ſayinge:
<q>Fides tua te ſaluam fecit. Vade in pace.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Thy fayth hath made thee ſafe,<note place="margin">Chriſt is a ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toure of his owne woorde.</note> or hathe ſaued thee, go thy waye in peace. How had fayeth ſaued her, but becauſe that throughe it, ſhe hadde obtayned remyſſion of ſynnes? In dede ſhe did afterwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des declare the ſame fayeth by the earneſt loue that ſhe dyd beare too Chriſte. And as for the other ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, I maruayle that they be not aſhamed to aleadge it. For, ye ſhall fynde it thus written in the prouerbes,<note place="margin">Prou. 10. cha.</note> from whence the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtell borowed it:
<q>Odium vitia detegit, charitas autem operit multitudinem peccatorum:</q>
               </p>
               <p>That is to ſaye: hatered doethe open, and dyſcouer faultes, but loue doethe couer the multitude of ſynnes.</p>
               <p>What other thinge canne we learne of this ſayinge of the wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:12849:35"/> manne, but that as hatered doeth moue vs, to caſte oure breethren in the tethe, and to vpbrayed them with the offences that they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit agaynſte vs: ſo loue hydeth and pardoneth the faultes, iniuryes &amp; wrongs that are done vnto vs, be they neuer ſo greate? In the ſame ſenſe did the holy Apoſtell take it, as it doeth manifeſtlye appeare by the cyrcumſtaunces of the place. But the enemies of the truth care not what they ſaye,<note place="margin">How the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the truth</note> ſo that they ſeme to ſaye ſome thinge. They aleadge the ſcryptures, as the blinde man caſteth his ſtaffe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDI.</speaker>
               <p>Ye teach that afore a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be iuſtified through faith in Chriſt he can do no good works, yea that all that he doeth is ſinne, though it ſemeth neuer ſo good.</p>
               <p>Nowe put the caſe that a Turke or heathen were deſirous to heare <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiecti∣on. </seg>5</label> the worde of God, and to knowe the goſpell of oure ſauioure Ieſu Chriſte. Woulde ye not coumpte
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12849:35"/> thys a good woorke?<note place="margin">Gardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt doctoure Barnes.</note> And yet ye wyll not ſaye, that he is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye iuſtifyed, for as muche as he doethe not yet beleaue in Chriſte.</p>
               <p>Beſydes thys, we haue the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Cornelius, of whome afore hee dyd beleeue in Chriſte, Luke wryteth after this manner: And the Aungell ſayed vnto him:<note place="margin">Act. 10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thy prayers and thyne almes, are come vp in too remembraunce before God.</p>
               <p>Theſe wordes did the Aungell ſpeake vnto Cornelius afore that he hearde Peter, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, afore that he beleued in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>What canne we gather of thys but that a man may do good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, afore he hathe fayth, and he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther throughe iuſtified?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPELVS.</speaker>
               <p>By oure brother Philalethes leaue, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> and vnder his correction: I wyll take vpon me to aunſwer thys obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that our neyghbour Dydimus
<pb facs="tcp:12849:36"/> hath broughte in nowe. I woulde fayne, neyghbour Dydimus that ye ſhould aunſwer me to this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion: Can a tree bringe foorthe good frute,<note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> afore it be made good?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDI.</speaker>
               <p>As no good tree canne bringe foorthe euyll frute, ſo can no yll tree brynge foorthe good fruyte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPE.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ephe. 2. Io. 15.</note>And what are we afore we be graffed in Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDI.</speaker>
               <p>As the holye Apoſtell doeth wryte: we are by oure owne nature the chyldren of wrath.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPELVS.</speaker>
               <p>And howe are we graffed in Chriſt? Or how are wee made braunches of the true vyne?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>I graunte that we are graffed in Chriſte, and made brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches of the true vine by faith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPE.</speaker>
               <p>Excepte then we haue fayeth we can not be graffed in Chriſte, nor made braunches of the true vyne. But oneleſſe we be graffed in Chriſte, we can not be
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12849:36"/> good trees, and if we be not good trees, we can bringe foorthe no good fruite. Againe: are not theſe the Apoſtels wordes:
<q>Quicquid ex fide non eſt peccatum eſt.<note place="margin">Ro. 14.</note>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>What ſoeuer is not of faythe, is ſynne: And withoute fayth,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> it is impoſſible to pleaſe God</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDI.</speaker>
               <p>What wyll ye ſay then of this turke or heathen, that hath a deſire to heare the word of God, and to knowe the goſpell of oure ſauioure Ieſu Chriſt, and parad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture doeth therefore take vpon him a long and parilous iourney?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EV.</speaker>
               <p>I ſaye, that the ſame Turke or heathen, maye of a vaine curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitye haue a deſyre to heare Gods worde, and the goſpell of Chriſte,<note place="margin">Act. 17.</note> as the Athenians,<note place="margin">why y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians woulde heare Paulles doctrine.</note> and the ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that were in theyr citye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge moued with vayne curioſity, wer deſirous to heare the doctrine of Paule, and for the ſame cauſe brought him to the ſtrete of Mars. Or as we oure ſelues are deſirous
<pb facs="tcp:12849:37"/> to know ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge hiſtories that we neuer redde before. We reade in the hiſtories that mani of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciente Philophers, did take vpon them long and perilous iourneies that they mighte learne the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Egiptians, and of the Caldees. But let vs by waye of reaſonninge, graunte that he doth it not of a vayne curioſitye, yet afore he be graffed in Chriſte, he remaineth ſtyll a dampnable tree, and therefore, his fruite can not be good: howe dare ye then call it a good worke? Theſe bee the wordes of Saynte Auguſtyne:<note place="margin">Li. ad boni fa. 3. cap. 5.</note>
                  <q>Religio noſtra iuſtos ab iniuſtis non ope rum, ſed ipſa fidei lege diſceruit, ſine qua etiam que videntur bona opera, in pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta conuertuntur.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Oute religion, ſayeth he, doeth not diſcerne the ryghteous from the vnrighteouſe by the lawe of woorkes, but by the verye lawe of faythe, wythoute the whyche yea thoſe workes, that ſeme good workes, are turned into ſynnes.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:12849:37"/>
               <p>And in an other place, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth the ſtudye and endeuoure of thoſe menne, that be not in the waye (but who is the waye, ſaue he only that ſayeth: I am the way, the truthe, and the life?<note place="margin">Ioa, 14.</note>) vntoo a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>goynge a ſtraye. For, the more earneſtlye (ſayth he) a man doeth renne beynge oute of the waye,<note place="margin">prefa. in Pſal. 31.</note> the farther doeth hee goo, frome the ſcope or marke, and ſo is made more miſerable. Therefore, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is to halte in the waye, than to renne out of the waye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>Ye can not ſaye ſo of Cornelius. For,<note place="margin">The hiſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry of Co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nelius.</note> the Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell ſayeth playnly, that his prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and almes, are come vp in too remembraunce before God. And this was afore he heard the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge of the goſpell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPELVS.</speaker>
               <p>And I wyll haue no better ſcriptures for too proue that Cornelius had fayeth. For, ſith that his praiers &amp; almes wer acceptable in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of God,
<pb facs="tcp:12849:38"/> and that withoute faythe it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to pleaſe God: it is moſte ſure that Cornelius was not with oute faythe. But we wyll heare Saynte Auguſtine touchinge that matter.<note place="margin">Auguſt. de predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione ſancto rum. capi. 7</note> 
                  <hi>Nec tamen</hi> (ſayeth hee) <hi>ſine fide aliqua donabat, et orabat, quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid et antequam in Chriſtum crederet, et cum crederet et quum credidiſſet ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus eſt Cornelius, totum deo dandum eſt, ne quis extollatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That is to ſaye: yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge, he neyther gaue nor prayed wythoute ſome fayethe. What ſoeuer Cornelius did worke afore he beleeued in Chriſte, and when he did beleue, and after that he beleued, all the whole muſt be geuen or attributed vnto God, leſt any man ſwel, or be puft vp: what ſhoulde we requyre any more? By the wordes of the Aungell, we do learne, that Cornelius both prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to God, and that his prayers were hearde. But how coulde he haue prayed vnto God, oneleſſe he had beleued on him alreadye?
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12849:38"/> For, thus doeth the Apoſtle write:<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note>
                  <q>Quomodo inuocabunt, in quem non crediderunt?</q>
               </p>
               <p>How ſayth he, ſhall they call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they do not beleue?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>I holde my ſelfe well ſatyſfyed in this poynte, I prayſe the liuinge God therefore. But I woulde fayne heare of you, brother Philalethes, which he the frutes of this our iuſtification, whiche we obtayne through faith onely in Chriſt, without any me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites or deſeruinge going before: and before whiche, all that we do (ſemethe it neuer ſo gorgeouſe in oure ſighte) is but mere ſynne in the ſighte of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>The frutes of this oure iuſtification,<note place="margin">The frutes of our iuſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</note> are exceadinge greate: Yea they are ineſtimable. For, god doeth not iuſtifie vs, nor yet deliuer vs from oure ſins to this ende, that we beinge iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ſhoulde by oure yll lyfe diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure his name, or blemiſhe his
<pb facs="tcp:12849:39"/> grace, aſthoughe he did not deteſt and abhorre ſynne, but that we ſhoulde ſerue to the glory of him, that hath wroughte oure ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.<note place="margin">The firſt frute of oure iuſty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fication.</note> The firſte fruite then of oure iuſtification is that the glorye of the righteouſneſſe of God maye be declared and ſette foorthe. Thys doeth the Apoſtell meane, when he ſayeth: They are iuſtyfied fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye by his grace, throughe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, whyche is in Chriſte Ieſu, whome God hath ſet foorth to be apourchaſſer of mercye, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe fayth in his bloude, too de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his righteouſneſſe,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.</note> by the forgeueneſſe of ſynnes. Agayne: Abraham dyd not doubte of the promes of God through vnbeleue, but was ſtrengthened in the faith and gaue glorye to God, beinge fullye aſſured,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> that he which had promiſſed, was able to do it. He therefore, that doethe beleeue the promſies of god, doth gloryfy him, geuing him the glory of truth and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12849:39"/> of power or might. And to this end, is he iuſtified,<note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond frute of our iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Rom. 5.</note> that the glorye of his goodneſſe may be ſet foorth. The ſecond is the peace of our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, wherof the Apoſtel ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth on this maner: We being iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified throughe faithe, haue peace toward God throughe oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EV.</speaker>
               <p>Where this peace is,<note place="margin">The peace of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience doeth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering or doubtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of minde.</note> there can be no place for wauering or doubtfulnes, which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcole men of our time, are wont to teach. For, doubtfulnes, and thys peace of conſcience, are altogether repugnaunt one to an other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>We haue not onely by iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, peace of conſcience but alſo a reioycinge, whiche can in no wiſe ſtand with doubtfulnes. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by do we reioyce vnder the hope of the glory of God,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> &amp; alſo in tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. It is ſo farre of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that we ought to doubt of the grace of god in Chriſt Ieſu, that rather he wyll haue vs to be at peace with him in our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences, &amp; to reioyce fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our
<pb facs="tcp:12849:40"/> very heartes vnder the hope of his glorye, and therefore doeth he iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifye vs freelye throughe fayth in Chriſt.<note place="margin">The thyrde frute of our iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</note> Thirdely this iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doeth tende alſo and pertayne to the glory of them that be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, as the Apoſtel him ſelfe doth teſtifye, ſayinge: Whom he hath ordayned before, them hath he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and whome he hathe called, them hath he iuſtified,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> and whom he hath iuſtified, them hathe he glorified.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDI.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiecti∣on. </seg>6</label> Theſe thinges are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Apoſtell, aſthoughe the iuſtified, were alreadye in the full poſſeſſion of their glory. For theſe are his wordes: whome he hathe iuſtifyed, them hath he alſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. But I am of opinion, that they that bee iuſtyfied throughe faythe in Chriſte, ſhall not haue their full glorye, vntill the ſecond comminge of the ſonne of manne, who wyll then tranſfourme and chaunge theyr vyle bodyes, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12849:40"/> make them lyke vnto his glorious bodye:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRA.</speaker>
               <p>Ye muſte vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> that the holye ghoſte vſeth this maner of ſpeakinge, for too declare the certayntye and infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of Gods promiſes. For, when God doethe promyſſe anye thinge,<note place="margin">The cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynetye of Gods promiſſe.</note> we maye be as ſure and certayne of it, as if it were alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye perfourmed and fulfilled. Sith then that God hathe promyſſed to glorifie them, whome he doth iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie throughe faythe in his ſonne Ieſu Chriſte: we muſt holde them for glorifyed alreadye, althoughe we do yet throughe hope looke for the glorye of the children of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>Ye haue ſayed verye well.<note place="margin">The .4. frute of our iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</note> Nowe the fourthe fruite of our iuſtification is this: God doth freelye by his grace iuſtifye vs in Chriſte, to the ende that we maye be both ſaued and made pertakers of eternall lyfe. For, thus writeth the Apoſtell in hys epiſtell to Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.
<pb facs="tcp:12849:41"/> But when the bountefulnes &amp; loue of God our ſauiour towarde man appeared. Not by the workes of righteouſneſſe, whiche we had done, but according to his merci he ſaued vs, by the waſſhinge of the new byrthe, &amp; the renewing of the holy ghoſt, which he ſhed on vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tli, through Ieſu Chriſt our ſauiour. That we beinge iuſtified by his grace, ſhould be made hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, according to the hope, of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall lyfe. Paull doeth call y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of this doctrin vndoubted, becauſe of the infallible truthe and certain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye of it. Therfore, I do greatly meruayl at the ſtupiditie or dulle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the enemies, whiche will not ſee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> comfortable light of thys doctrine, nor feele this ineſtimable grace, whiche they doe ſo ſore im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne or fight againſt in the elect and choſen of God.<note place="margin">The fifte frute of our iuſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</note> As for the fifth frute of our iuſtification, it doeth moſt chiefly pertayne, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holines of lyfe, &amp; to the ſtudie &amp; exerciſe of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12849:41"/> righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. Whereof the Apoſtle doth warne vs in the .vi. to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, ſaying: Now beinge made free from ſinne, and made ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts vnto God, ye haue youre fruyte in holines. And in the firſt to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Corin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thians, theſe be his wordes: be not deceyued:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.</note> Neither whoremongers nor Idolaters, nor aduoutrers &amp;c. ſhall inherite the kyngedome of God.<note place="margin">Why the ſpirit of Chriſt is geuen vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to them that be iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtified.</note> And ſuche were ſome of you but ye are waſſhed, but ye are ſanc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tified, but ye are iuſtified in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of the Lorde Ieſus: and by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of our God. By which wordes he doeth admoniſh them, that ſith they were iuſtified, they ought fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thenſfoorth to geue them ſelues to godlineſſe, to holineſſe of lyfe and to righteouſnes. And for this cauſe is the ſpirit of Chriſte geuen vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be iuſtyfied, that through hym they may be chaunged in too a neweneſſe of lyfe. Which new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, beynge receyued by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite of God, is not the iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12849:42"/> it ſelfe, but a fruyte of the iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>Thys doctrine ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kethe me nowe better and better. And truelye when I heare you to ſoundly ſpeake of iuſtification and of the frutes thereof, I can not but maruayle at the ſhameleſſe repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the ennemyes, whyche do ſtyll blowe abroade, that ye are vtter enemies of good workes, of holyneſſe of life, and of all Godly exerciſes of righteouſneſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRA.</speaker>
               <p>What is it, that they wyll be aſhamed of, ſaue on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye of well doynge, and of well ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge?<note place="margin">Whereof the enemi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es of the truth be aſhamed.</note> They haue put on whores faces: and therefore, althoughe they be taken in a manifeſtlie, thei be no more a ſhamed of it, than a common ſtrompet is a ſhamed of hyr filthye acte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>That all the woorlde maye know how ſhamefully they do miſrep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rte vs, I wyll here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and ſetfoorthe what we doo
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12849:42"/> teache commonly of good works,<note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preachers touching good wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes.</note> and of the true vſes of them. Firſt we teache that as all things haue ben created of God not to this end that they ſhoulde be ydell and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, but too the ende that they ſhuld be profitable and good: ſo did he make and create man, not for to be ydell here;<note place="margin">Why ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> or for to be an vnprofitable burden of the earth, but to this ende, that euery one of vs, ſhoulde accordinge to his vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and callinge, worke thoſe thynges that be good and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The deuyll in dede by bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſynne,<note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill did peruert y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end of our creation, which Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne.</note> did peruert this end of oure creation, but Chriſt did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore it agayne, beinge ſente in too the worlde for to deſtroye the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of Sathan. By him we are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated or borne of newe, that beynge made newe creatures, we ſhoulde be profitable, and full of good workes. And therefore, the Apoſtel in the epiſtel to the Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, writeth on this maner:<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.</note> we
<pb facs="tcp:12849:43"/> are the workemanſhippe of God created in Chriſt Ieſus, vnto thoſe good workes, that God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for vs, for to walke in. And in the epiſtell to Titus: Who ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he, gaue him ſelfe for vs, that he mighte redeme vs from all ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitye,<note place="margin">Titus. 2.</note> and make vs a peculyar people vnto him ſelfe, being ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtlye geuen vntoo good workes.<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> Hereunto belonge the exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Chriſt and of the Apoſtels. Such as theſe are: let your light ſo ſhyne before men,<note place="margin">Gala. 6.</note> that they maye ſee your good woorks and glorify your father, whiche is in heauen. And in the epiſtel to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Galathians theſe are the Apoſtels wordes:<note place="margin">1, Timo. 3.</note> Let vs not ceaſſe to do good vnto al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but moſt ſpecialli to them, that are of the houſholde of faith. Are not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures geuen vntoo vs for the ſame purpoſe and vſe? The whole ſcripture ſaith Paull, is geuen by inſpiration of God, &amp; is profitable to teach, to improue, to correct and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12849:43"/> to inſtructe in righteouſneſſe, that the man of God maye be abſolute or ſound, beinge made perfect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all good woorkes. It is euydent then, that we be not ſo iuſtified by fayeth, that after iuſtyfication, we ſhould remayn, vnprofitable, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reyne, and vnfrutefull, but rather y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> geuing our ſelues without ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing &amp; intermiſſion to good works we ſhoulde aduaunce and farther the glorye of the grace of God, and ſet before all mennes eyes, as it were a cetayn light of a new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.<note place="margin">Similitude</note> Who doeth plant or ſet a tree or doeth dygge aboute the roote of it, to the ende that it ſhoulde only be a tre, and not rather to this end that it ſhould be a good tree, and bring foorthe good frutes. So, are we regenerated in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Why we be regene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rated in Chriſt.</note> &amp; iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, not to this end, that we ſhuld be only Chriſtians in name, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of euyll trees we ſhoulde be made good, and expreſſe that ſame good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that wee haue receaued of
<pb facs="tcp:12849:44"/> Chriſte, by good workes. When we teache theſe thinges, we doo neyther geue occaſion to the enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, to condempne iuſtelye the doctrine of iuſtification, as enemy of good workes, nor yet ought we to be blamed, although falſe goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelers doe rather liue like Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, than true Chriſtian men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDI.</speaker>
               <p>Who hauinge a crome or droppe of godlineſſe, can be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at this doctrine?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRA.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Who thei be that are offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at the doctrine of the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of faith</note>They onelye are offended at this mooſte true and wholſome doctrine which partely do rather ſeeke theyr own gaynes and lucre, than the ſaluation of the people: And partlye, beinge erecated or blynded wyth vayne ſuperſtition, do embrace, and ſet foorthe vnto other, mens dyueliſh inuentions for good workes. For, vnto them,<note place="margin">The good works of the papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes.</note> to heare euerye daye maſſe deuoutely, to lye proſtrate before dead images, and to mum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mell oute a number of prayers vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12849:44"/> certayne Soyntes, to go on pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimages, to buyld vp chanteries, and to cauſe Trentalles of Maſſes with diriges and other tromperye to be ſayed for the deade. Item to geue largelye of theyr ſubſtaunce and gooddes vntoo ydell prieſtes, mounkes, friers, and nonnes, too ſaye oure ladyes pſalter, to praye on beades, too vſe, obſerue and kepe phariſaicall faſtinges, wyth theyr popiſhe holye dayes, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lempne feaſtes, are the beſt works that can eyther be deuiſed or done, and whoſoeuer do ſpeake againſte thoſe workes,<note place="margin">They y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papyſtes good wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of ſin, and of moſt dete<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtable ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on. Rom. 14.</note> they are by and by taken for vtter ennemies of good workes, wheras if the thinge wer indifferentlye weyghed in the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen balaunce of Gods word, they ought rather to be coumpted ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes of ſynne, and of moſte dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable abhomination. For, what ſoeuer is not of faythe, is ſynne. But how ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe their gai painted workes be of faythe, ſith that they
<pb facs="tcp:12849:45"/> haue no grounde at all in Goddes worde? What gaye titles ſo euer then, they geue vnto them, it can not be denyed, but that they are moſt deteſtable ſynnes in the ſight of God, who wyll alowe none other kinde of religion, worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinge, and ſeruyce, than he him ſelfe, hath preſcribed and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his holye ſcriptures.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDI.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>7</label> What wil ye ſaye then of our good intentes? Wyl ye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempne them all? For, manye do thoſe works that ye ſpake of, euen now, of a good intente, thinkinge that they do high ſeruice vnto god Shall thys theyr good intente be imputed vnto them for ſynne?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EV.</speaker>
               <p>As concerning good intents, we haue this leſſon geuen vnto vs in the boke of God:<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> ye ſhall not do euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that which ſemeth vnto youe beſt:<note place="margin">Good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes.</note> I am the Lord thy God, that thinge onlye that I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund the, ſee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou doeſt it. Ad nothing vnto it, take nothinge away from
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:12849:45"/> it. We muſt not do then what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſemeth vnto vs beſt, but what ſoeuer the lord our God doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund and wylleth vs to doo: ſo that by this one place of Deutero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomye,<note place="margin">Deu. 12.</note> all good intentes that be not ruled by Gods word, are quite ouerthrowen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>It doeth well appeare by manye hiſtories of the Bible, how well God doeth lyke oure good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes.<note place="margin">Terrible and dread<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes.</note> In the .ix. and .x. chapters of Leuiticus, ye ſhall fynde thys wrytten: And there came a fyre oute frome the Lorde, and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vppon the altare, the burnte offering and the fat. Which when all the people ſawe, they gaue thankes and felle on theyr faces.</p>
               <p>But Nadab and Abihu, the ſonnes of Aaron, tooke eyther of them his cenſor, and put fire ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and put incens thereuppon, and offered ſtraunge fyre before the Lorde, whiche he had not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded them.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12849:46"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How our good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che haue no wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt in Goddes word are rewarded</note>Therefore a fyre wente from the Lorde and deuoured them, ſo they dyed before the Lord. Without all peraduenture, they dyd this of a good intent. For, onleſſe they had thoughte, that God woulde haue bene pleaſed with it, they woulde in no wyſe haue done it, yet ye ſee howe they were rewarded for it. Who, I praye you, readinge this hiſtorye, will not be affrayed too ſerue God otherwiſe than he doth appoynte in his worde? In the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond boke of Samuell,<note place="margin">2. Samu. 6.</note> it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that when Dauid wold bring the Arke to Ieruſalem, hee cauſed it to be put vpon a new cart (whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che doubtleſſe was moſt gorgeouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye trymmed, and drawen with the goodlyeſt and fayreſt cattell that coulde be gotten) Dauid and and the houſe of Iſraell playinge before the Lord on all inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes made of fyre, and on harpes, and on pſalteries, and on tymbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and on cornetts, and on
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12849:46"/> cimballes. But nowe marke the ende: when they came to Nachons threſhinge floore,<note place="margin">Vzzah ſmitten of the Lord.</note> Vzzah did put his hande, too the Arke of God, and helde it. For, the oxen dyd ſhake it. And the Lorde was very wroth with vzzah, and God ſmote him in the ſame place for his faut, and there he dyed by the Arke of God. Let Dauid expounde this matter, him ſelfe. In the firſt boke of the chronicles,<note place="margin">1. Para. 13.</note> theſe be his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des which he ſpake vnto the Leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: becauſe ye were not there at the fyrſt: the Lord our God made a breache or rent among vs. For we ſoughte him not after due order. This was the due order,<note place="margin">The or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that God had apoynted touching the Arke.</note> that ſhuld haue bene obſerued and kept. The Lorde God hath appoynted, that the Arke ſhould haue bene caryed vpon the ſhoulders of the Leuites. But what did Dauid? For a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altye, and to declare his greate zeale, that he bare to Gods religy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wold haue it to be caried vpon
<pb facs="tcp:12849:47"/> a goodlye chariot or waggon, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge beinge omitted or lefte of, that belonged to ſuch glorious ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nity, as ye haue learned before. Yet ye ſee how God did accepte it. As for Vzzah, no man can denye, but that he dyd of a good intente put foorth his hand to haue ſtayed the Arke,<note place="margin">Saul ſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth in de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fence of his diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</note> leaſt it ſhoulde through the ſtronglinge of the cattell haue fallen doune in to the myre. Who woulde not iudge that thys was wel done? And yet was he ſmitten of the Lorde, that hee dyed before the Arke. Wherby we learn what daunger it is too folowe good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes, or to doo anye thinge in good ſeruyce without hys expreſſe worde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe are very ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible and dreadfull examples, God graunte that wee maye haue the grace alwaies to remember them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>The hiſtorye of Saull, who was the firſt kinge of the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites, is yet more terrible. God
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12849:47"/> had geuen him a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement, that he ſhould ſmite Amaleke, and deſtroye all that pertayned vntoo them, and haue no compaſſion on them, but ſlaye both man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, both infante and ſuckeling, bothe oxe and ſhepe, bothe camell and aſſe.<note place="margin">The hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorye of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Saul.</note> But Saul and the people ſpared the beſt of the ſhepe, and of the oxen, for to ſacrifice them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lorde, and deſtroyed all the reſt. This did they of a good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente, in ſo muche that Saul ſtode in defenſe of the deede, ſayinge: I haue obeid the voyce of the Lord &amp; haue deſtroyed the Amalechites but the people toke of the ſpoyle, ſhepe and oxen, and the chiefeſt of the things, which ſhould haue ben deſtroyed for to offer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the Lord. Vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prophet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel anſwered: Hath the Lord as great pleaſyr in burnt offerings &amp; ſacrifice, as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the voice of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord is obeid? Behold to obey is better than ſacrifice, and too harkene is
<pb facs="tcp:12849:48"/> better than the fatte of rammes: But rebellion is as the ſynne of witchcrafte and diſobedience is as the wickednes of ydolatry. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, becauſe thou haſt caſt awaye the worde of the Lorde the Lorde hath alſo caſt thee awaye from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge king. Becauſe then that Saul dyd rather folowe his good intent than the commaundemente, and worde of the Lorde, therefore his kingedome, was not onelye rente from him, and geuen to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure, that was better than he, but alſo the ſpirit of the Lorde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted frome him,<note place="margin">1. Samu. 16</note> and an euyll ſpiritte ſente of the Lorde vexed hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>Are theſe the frutes of our good intents? From hencefoorth God wylling, I wyll endeuoure my ſelfe, to harken vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>too the voyce of the Lorde, to obey hys commaundementes, and too ſerue him as he wil be ſerued. For beſydes thoſe terrible and dreade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12849:48"/> hiſtoryes, I remember the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge of Chriſt, where he ſayeth: They worſhip me in vayne, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge the doctrines,<note place="margin">Mat. 15.</note> and precepts of men. Wherby it is made moſte manifeſt and playne, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion worſhippinge and ſeruice of God, whiche is errected and ſet vp after the phancies and dreams of mennes headdes, is both vayne and abhominable before the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>Syth that the good woorkes of the popecacholikes do rather deſerue the name of ſynne and of deteſtable abhomynation before God, than of good works, as it hath ben by you ſufficientlye proued alreadye: I woulde fayne hear which be the true good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes,<note place="margin">Which be the true good wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes, that God doth requyre of vs.</note> that are required of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>The true good workes, are voyde of all ſuperſtition, they are alligated or bounde neyther to place, nor to the perſonnes, nor to
<pb facs="tcp:12849:49"/> tyme. For, they are as certayne frutes of our whole life, teſtifying of the goodneſſe of oure hart, and expreſſinge the nature of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father, whiche not onely of the faythfull, but of the very infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delles are reckenned and taken for good workes, and miniſter occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto them, to glorifye our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whyche is in heauen. The works of fayth, working through charity and loue, are good works. For, God doeth worke them in vs and by vs. Them doth our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt ſet oute in the .xxv. chapiter of Mathewe,<note place="margin">Why the good wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes of mercy are moſt chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flye ſet foorth vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs.</note> ſayinge: I was a hungerd and ye gaue me meate, I was a thyrſt, and ye gaue me drincke, I was naked, and ye clothed me, I was harborleſſe and ye harboured me, I was ſicke and in priſon, and ye viſited me. The holye apoſtell likewyſe, in the .v. and .vi. chapter of the Epiſtel to the Galatians doth ſufficiently teache
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12849:49"/> vs, what be the good workes, that God doth require of vs, But what ſhould I aleadge one text or two, ſyth that the whole ſcriptures, doe euery where, exhorte vs ſtyll vnto good workes?<note place="margin">Which be the good workes, that God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for vs too walke in.</note> What thoſe good workes be Paule doeth declare in the ſeconde to the Epheſyans, when he ſayth: We are the worke manſhyp of God created in Chriſt Ieſu, vnto thoſe good works, that God hathe prepared for vs, for to walke in.</p>
               <p>Yf onye nowe ſhould aſke, what be thoſe good woorkes, that he hathe prepared for vs for to walke in? I woulde aunſwer, that all thoſe woorkes, that God doethe bydde and commaunde vs in hys holye and ſacred worde, are thoſe good woorkes, that he hathe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for vs, for to walke in.</p>
               <p>And thoſe, I ſaye, ought onelye to be called good workes and non other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:12849:50"/>
               <speaker>DYDI.</speaker>
               <p>And is there nothing els to be marked in this doctrine of good workes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>Beſides that which hath ben ſaied already, this ought to be conſidered: that is, in what re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpecte, thoſe workes, whiche in them ſelues are good, be done of men.<note place="margin">Why all they that do thoſe good wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes that God hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his worde do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the prayſe of well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge.</note> For, they doo not by and by deſerue the prayſe and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of good works, that do them: and that, becouſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they do ſhote at a wrong marke in doyng of them. For manye be wonte to feade the hungrye, too geue drincke to the thyrſty, to cloth the naked, and ſo foorthe: but do they it for any loue that they beare to god, and to their neyghbour, and for to ſhew theyr obedience towardes his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements? Nay, they do it, for to be glorifyed of men. Some agayn do theſe woorkes of charitye, that by them, thruſtinge Chriſt out of his roume, they maye merite and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue heauen, as though eternall
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12849:50"/> and euerlaſtinge life, were not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readye fullye and moſt perfectlye pourchaſſed vnto vs, by the meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the death, paſſion and bloud ſheddynge of the onelye begotten ſon of God,<note place="margin">Heb. 7.</note> or as though Chriſt for al his euerlaſting prieſthode, could not fully and to the vttermoſt ſaue them, that by him do come vntoo God. Theſe laſt,<note place="margin">Mercena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and hirelings</note> maye be called mercenaryes or hyrlinges. For, as muche as they do all, that they do, in reſpecte of reward: the hope of the whych reward beyng taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye, they would not geue a cup of colde water. There be ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne that doo good workes, but wherfore? For feare leſt thei ſhuld, if they did nothing at al, come in to purgatory, after their death.<note place="margin">The vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papiſtes.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPELVS.</speaker>
               <p>And verely there be many, which doo openly affyrme, that the preachynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt Purgatorye, hathe bene a playn ouerthrowing of good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. For the fear (ſay they) of thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:12849:51"/> bytter paynes, that the poore ſely ſoules, be fayne to ſuffer there, hath cauſed manye, to do that, that they woulde not haue done, if thei had bene wythout that feare.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>Why do they not rather feare the vnquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheable fyer of hell, that oure ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uioure Ieſus Chriſte doeth ſpeake of,<note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> ſayinge: Departe ye frome me, ye curſed in to the fyer euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge, whyche is prepared for the Deuyll and hys Aungelles?<note place="margin">Luc. 16.</note> For, I was a hungerd and ye gaue me no meate, I was a thyrſt and ye gaue me no drincke.<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.53.</note> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Hereunto myghte be added, the hyſtory of the ryche glutton, who for his vnmercyfulneſſe was thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen headlonge in too the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe pytte of hell. Theſe be they, that wyll be affrayed, where no feare is, but where there is a iuſt cauſe of feare, there they be neuer a whytte affrayed.</p>
               <p>How be it, we maye well lykene
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12849:51"/> them, that worke for feare of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nithemente,<note place="margin">They y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worke for feare are like vnto lewde ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uauntes.</note> vnto ſlaues or lewde ſeruauntes, whyche, oneleſſe it were for feare of ſtripes. woulde do nothynge at all. But we muſt be chyldren and not ſeruauntes: We muſte folowe the example of oure ſauyoure Ieſus Chriſte, who althoughe he was mooſte ſure of heauen, and dyd in no wyſe feare helle, yet dyd he neuer ceaſſe too doe good vnto all menne,<note place="margin">In doyng of good workes we muſt folow the example of Chriſt.</note> whyles he was here conuerſaunte in the earthe amongeſt them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>If, we oughte to doe good woorkes, neyther for hope of rewarde nor for feare of the endeleſſe tormentes of helle fyer, wherefore ſhoulde we doe them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALE.</speaker>
               <p>There be fyue pryncypall cauſes whye the chyldren of God oughte too be earneſtlye geuen vnto good woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. The fyrſte is, that the
<pb facs="tcp:12849:52"/> glory of our heauenly father may be ſet foorth, as Chriſt him ſelfe doth teache vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> ſayinge: L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ your lyght ſo ſhyne before menne, that they maye ſee your good workes, and glorifye your father which is in heauen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRA.</speaker>
               <p>If there wer non other vſe or profyt of good works, than the ſame that Chriſt did tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che vs: the teachers of good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, oughte in no wiſe, to laye to our charge the puttynge doune of good workes, becauſe wee denye that they iuſtifye. For, as this is the chyefeſt deſire of the fayeth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that they maye glorifye the name of the Lorde theyr God, ſo do they coumpte it, to be the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt vantage vnto them, if thei can glorify hym by their good works, althoughe they gette none other profyt, by theyr Godly ſtudy and exerciſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>This is the marke, that our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt did
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12849:52"/> ſhoote at: whoſe example, as I ſaid before, we ought to folowe in this thinge. Nowe the ſeconde cauſe that oughte to moue vs to do good workes, or the ſecond vſe of them, is, that by them, we maye in our conſciences be certifyed of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, and callinge: not that our election and callinge do depend or hange of good workes for, how coulde that be, ſyth that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell writeth on this maner:<note place="margin">2. Timo. 1.</note> Who hath ſaued vs, and called vs with an holy callyng, not accordinge to our workes, but accordinge to his owne purpoſe and grace, whiche was geuen to vs throughe Chriſt Ieſus, before the world was?) but becauſe that by them, we do daily more and more proue or feele the grace and vertue of Chriſt:<note place="margin">Euil wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the malitiouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe of our harts</note> as on the contrary ſyde, euyll workes do daily more and more expreſſe, and declare the malitiouſeneſſe of our hartes. And to this pertaineth, the ſayinge of the holye Apoſtell
<pb facs="tcp:12849:53"/> Saynte Peter: Wherefore, ſaith hee, geue rather dyligence, too make youre callynge and ellecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>All be it then our election is ſure ynoughe in it ſelf, for as muche as God canne not chaunge:<note place="margin">Note.</note> yet we muſt confyrme it in oure ſelues by the frutes of the ſpirit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>Ye do well vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande the meanynge of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell. I can you thanke, brother Albion, I iudge nowe my labour well beſtowed. The thyrde vſe of good workes is, that by them our fayeth is excerciſed, nouryſhed, encreaſed and ſtrengthenned. And therefore, thus doeth the Apoſtell write vnto his diſciple Timothee: Styrre vp the gyft of God,<note place="margin">2. Timo. 1.</note> which is in thee. Here, fayth is called the gifte of God,<note place="margin">Whye faith is ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kened vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſpark</note> whiche is as a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſparkle or flame, kyndeled in our harts: Which Sathan and the fleſhe laboure to quenche, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12849:53"/> therefore we muſte nouriſhe, and ſtyr it vp, by continuall exerciſes, of the deedes of charitye. For, as fyer by caſtinge in of woodde, is augmented and made bygger: ſo in the Chriſtians,<note place="margin">Similitude</note> bothe Godlines and faythe, is by doynge of good workes, nouriſhed and made liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Fourthly by our good works, our neighbours are prouoked vnto the like ſtudye and loue of godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, when they do ſee in vs certain lyuely examples of it, which they maye folowe. So Paule in hys ſecond Epiſtell to the Corinthians ſayeth:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 9.</note> youre zeale (ſpeakinge of almes) hath prouoked very many. And in the epiſtel to the Hebreues Let vs, ſayeth he,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note> conſider one an other, to prouoke vnto loue and vnto good workes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EV.</speaker>
               <p>If this had ben obſerued and kepte amonge Chriſtians, by this time, both the Turks &amp; the Iewes with al the paynims in the world, would haue ben wonne to Chriſt.
<pb facs="tcp:12849:54"/> But as long as we vſe our ſelues after this ſame ſorte, we ſhall ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther become Turks and Painims than they Chriſtians.<note place="margin">What cauſeth the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes and paynims to abhor Chriſtes religion.</note> Suche fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of life, ſuche vntrue dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge, deceate, fraude and periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, ſuch ydolatrye and ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they do ſee dayly to raygne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge vs, that it is no maruayle, if they do abhorre altogether oure religion. We go about to conquere them by force of armes, but we ſee that through our ſynnes, they are growen ſo mighty that they be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, if God doeth not ſet his heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinge hand, to ouer renne all the whole worlde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>This that ye ſaye, is moſt true. And vntyll a true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation be hadde, and better a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendmente of lyfe be ſeene in vs, thei wil neuer embrace Chriſt nor his Goſpell. But to our purpoſe: this is the fift vſe of good workes, that by them Chriſt is releaued in his poore and nedy members, yea
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12849:54"/> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſocieti, and felowſhip of men is mayntained. For haue we not al nede one of an other? Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be not menne, but vayne ſhadowes of men,<note place="margin">Vain ſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dowes of men.</note> which through oute all their life time, are found to be ydell, ſo that they ſeme to be borne for nothinge elles but for to conſume the frutes of the earth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>I woulde gladly learne,<note place="margin">Whether our good works be accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto God or not.</note> whether theſe oure good workes do pleaſe God or not, and why they be acceptable vnto him, ſyth that the profyt of them doeth redounde vnto vs altogether.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>That our good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes do pleaſe God, it is euydente and playn by the wordes of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtell, where he ſayeth:<note place="margin">Coloſſe.</note> That ye might walke worthy of the Lord, and pleaſe him in all thinges,<note place="margin">The cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes why our good works do pleaſe God.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge frutefull in all good workes. They therefore, that be frutefull in all kynde of good workes, doe pleaſe God in all thinges. The cauſes are manifeſt enough. It is
<pb facs="tcp:12849:55"/> ſo in dede, that the dyuine maieſty of God hathe no neede neyther of oure good wordes, nor yet of oure good workes: yet thoſe thynges, that are well done of vs, do pleaſe him. Fyrſte becauſe they be the frutes of fayth. He that aloweth the fayeth of his people, ſhoulde not hee alſo alowe the fruytes of their fayth? As he doeth reproue all workes that be done without fayth, ſo doeth he alowe all maner of works, that do procede of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere fayeth and true beliefe. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly our good workes do pleaſe hym, becauſe they bee done and wrought by hys ſpirite.<note place="margin">Phi. 2.</note> For, as the holy Apoſtell doeth teſtifye: he worketh in vs both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> will and the dede, accordinge to hys good wyl. And therfore ſaint Auguſtine ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ryghte well,<note place="margin">Augu.</note> that God doeth croune in vs, hys owne workes. We canne not denye but that the works that we do by the ſpiryt of god, are bi reaſon of our imperfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12849:55"/> vnperfectely good, yet for as muche as they come of hym, it canne not be, but that they muſt pleaſe hym, as beynge the righte author of them. Thyrdely that, whiche the Godlye do, they do it for Gods ſake, beynge deſirous to gratifye him in all thinges. Wyll not he, thinke ye, accept this their good wyll, and deſyre or mynde, that they haue to pleaſe him? We do not here ſpeake of thoſe,<note place="margin">Note.</note> that neyther of a pure fayeth, nor by the ſprytte of God, but of mere ſuperſtition, and of a generall cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, do woorke manye thinges, thynkinge thereby to pleaſe God, whereas they do hyghly diſpleaſe him. This ſaying of Chriſt is not vnknowen: They worſhippe me in vayne teachinge the doctrynes and preceptes of men.<note place="margin">Math. 15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Herein bothe the Iewes, and falſe Chriſtyans doe mooſte ſhamefullye erre. Fourthelye, God oure heauenlye father doethe
<pb facs="tcp:12849:56"/> accordynge to his ryghteouſneſſe loue al works that be good, righte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſe and iuſte: as on the contrary ſide, he doeth not onely deteſt and abhorre the vngodlyneſſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſeneſſe of a wicked hart, but alſo all the frutes of vngodly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and of vnrighteouſeſſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what tytelles ſo euer they be aduaunced, and ſet foorthe. Thou doeſt hate,<note place="margin">Pſal. 5.</note> ſaieth Dauid, all that worke iniquitye thou ſhalt deſtroy them all that ſpeake leaſinge. And in the Actes of the Apoſtelles thus doeth Peter ſaye:<note place="margin">Act. 10.</note> Emonge all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions whoſoeuer doeth feare God is acceptable vnto him. Fyftely, becauſe that God is moſt true, yea rather the truthe it ſelfe, our good dedes do therefore pleaſe him, be cauſe that they proceade of true godlyneſſe, and of an vnfaygned ſayth, which aboue all thinges, God is wonte to regarde and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte. For, as all hipocrites are deteſtable bothe before God, and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12849:56"/> before men: ſo contrarywiſe God loueth truthe, not onely in thoſe thinges that are well done of the faithfull, but alſo in them, that do truely and without al diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation confeſſe and acknowledge theyr ſynnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRA.</speaker>
               <p>Truely, ſyth that it is ſo manifeſt,<note place="margin">How ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly the cauſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſed oughte to moue vs to do good workes.</note> that the good works of the faythfull do pleaſe God, we oughte with all oure whole ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to geue our ſelues vnto good workes, for as muche as they be not onely many and ſondrye way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es profitable vnto the whole miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall bodye of Chriſt, which is his church, but are alſo, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue reherſed, moſt pleaſaunt and acceptable vnto the lyuinge Lord oure heauenlye father. For, that man hath but ſmall Godlyneſſe in him ſelfe whom theſe two cauſes, can not moue to do wel. Agayn: he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gapeth onely in doynge of good workes, after a recompence or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, or reckeneth for a merite,
<pb facs="tcp:12849:57"/> whatſoeuer he doeth, thinkinge that God is therefore bound vnto him, hathe but a mercenaries hart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Whether our good workes ſhallbe re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warded or not.</note>And ſhal our good workes be neuer a whytte rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>I wyll not ſaye ſo. For althoughe the liuing God be debtoure vnto no man, yet of his goodneſſe, he doeth promyſſe and geue a reward vnto the good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the faythfull. And therefore we haue theſe ſayings in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures:<note place="margin">Math. 5.10.</note> Reioyce, and be glad, for, youre rewarde is great in heauen, agayne: he that geueth to one of theſe my lytle ones a cup of coulde water in my name: Verely, I ſay vnto you, he ſhall not loſe his re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward.<note place="margin">Heb. 6.</note> And in the Epiſtel to the He<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brewes: God ſayeth he, is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſe that he ſhould forgette our laboure. Nowe we muſt not thinke that this reward is promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto our good workes, becauſe
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12849:57"/> of the dignitye and worthineſſe of them (for are not theſe our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt his wordes.<note place="margin">Luc. 17.</note> When ye haue done what ſo euer I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde you, ſaye ye, we are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes? But becauſe that throughe fayth, we haue fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, with the onlye begotten ſonne of God,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> whereby it cometh to paſſe, that his perfect obedience is imputed vnto vs for our owne, and al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is wanting, and lacking in vs &amp; in our workes is moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fettly ſupplied by it. As the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell doeth teſtifye, ſayinge: Chriſt is the fulfyllinge of the lawe, for to iuſtifye all them that do beleue. And in an other place: Chriſt is made vnto vs of God, holines wiſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, righteouſneſſe, and redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption.</p>
               <p>Secondely our good dedes ſhall be rewarded or crouned becauſe that god of hys mere mercy hath bound him ſelfe thereto by his promiſſes, as it hath ben declared before by the
<pb facs="tcp:12849:58"/> textes that wee haue aleadged. Wherunto doeth ſaynt Auguſtin agree,<note place="margin">Augu. in pſa. 32.109 and in ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye other places.</note> where he ſayeth:
<q>Fidelis dominus, qui ſe nobis debitorem fecit, non aliquid a nobis accipiendo, ſed omnia nobis promittendo.</q>
               </p>
               <p>That is to ſaye: The Lorde is faithfull who hath made him ſelfe a debtoure vnto vs, not by recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge anye thynge of vs, but by promiſſinge vnto vs all thinges. Here we learn, how god is become debtour vnto vs,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.</note> and hath bounde him ſelfe, to croune or reward our good works, not by receauing any thinge of vs (for, what haue we, that we haue not receaued,<note place="margin">Rom. 11.</note> and if we haue receaued, whye doe we boeſte or glory, aſthough we had not receaued? Agayne: who gaue him fyrſte, and he ſhall be recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed?) but by his faythfull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes, whiche he hath made vnto his electe and choſen people.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDI.</speaker>
               <p>What ſo euer ye ſaye of the reward, I meane: why and wherefore it is geuen vnto oure
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12849:58"/> good workes, yet it can not ſinke in to my headde, but that we may by them meryte or deſerue ſome parte of oure ſaluation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>How coulde that be,<note place="margin">The cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes why we can by our good wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes merit no part of oure ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</note> neyghboure Dydimus, ſyth that we are not our owne men, but are wholye the Lordes, of whome we haue bene created fyrſt, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes redemed from ſynne, and eternall death, by the price of his bloude? Ye are bought, ſayeth. S. Paule wyth a greate price. And in an other place: We are the Lords, whether we lyue or dye. None of vs do lyue vnto him ſelfe. What merite then canne we pretende,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.</note> or what rewarde canne we claime of him, whoſe we are wholye or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together? Therfore, eyther let vs take away this abſolute power of God, which he hath ouer vs all, as ouer his owne peculiar good,<note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note> or let vs acknowledge, that it is not meete for ſeruauntes to boaſte and bragge of theyr meryttes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte
<pb facs="tcp:12849:59"/> theyr maſter, nor yet to aſke for rewardes. If the maſter doeth accepte the faithfulneſſe and diligence of his ſeruaunt, and doth impute it vnto him for a meritte, iudginge him worthye to be made free: that oughte to be attributed vnto his goodneſſe, and not vnto dutye, as thoughe he were bound vnto him therefore,<note place="margin">We are all deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God &amp; when we haue don all that we can do we haue but paied our debt.</note> becauſe that he is faitfull, and ſerueth fayeth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and truly. For, the ſeruaunt ſo doinge, doeth but his dutye, and onleſſe he ſhoulde do it, he were worthy of puniſhement. No man, excepte he be of a ſingular good nature, wyll geue thankes to his debtour, becauſe that he hath pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him his debte. And the debtour were verye impudente or ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, if he, as thoughe he had wel merited, woulde therefore claime a rewarde, becauſe that he hadde payed his debte. He that beinge a ſeruaunte or a debtour, doeth that thinge, which he is bounde to do,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:12849:59"/> can boaſte of no merite. But ſuch are we al; yea when we be alredy made righteous, and do the things that we are commaunded to doe. Let neuer this ſayinge of Chriſte, go out of oure myndes. When ye haue done, what ſo euer I haue commaunded you, ſaye ye we are vnprofitable ſeruaunts. But how manye of vs, canne do the tenthe parte of that, whiche we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, with ſuch a perfection, as God requireth? What can we then meritte or deſerue? Adde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, that we are not onelye ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts and debtours to God in al things, but alſo ſo void of al good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and Godly ſtrength, that we can not as muche as thinke a good thinge,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.</note> muche leſſe that of oure ſelues we ſhoulde be able too per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it in dede, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue nede that al our ſufficiency or ableneſſe be miniſtred vnto vs, by the diuine grace of god. Therfore the Apoſtle doth plainlye affirme, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is God,<note place="margin">Phi. 2.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12849:60"/> that worketh in vs both the wyl &amp; the deede, accordinge to his good wyll. That then, we wyll anye thinge that good is, and do in dede perfourme it, it cometh not of our owne wyll and ſtrength, but it is both the wyll and worke of God, workynge in vs accordinge to his good pleaſure. Whence then haue we oure fayth, loue, hope, the fear of God, patience in aduerſitye? Whence haue we oure good wyl, and ſtrength to doe good? If we haue theſe thinges of our ſelues, we haue wherein to glorye or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce. But if we haue al theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the gratuite and fre grace of God, what doth it folow, but that we ought rather to geue thankes to the goodneſſe of God, than to <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiecti∣on. </seg>8,</label> boaſte of our merites?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPE.</speaker>
               <p>I was once in a place, where they made this obiection agaynſte me. Be not theſe, ſaye they, the wordes of the Apoſtell:<note place="margin">2. Timo. 4.</note> I haue foughte a good
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:12849:60"/> fight, and haue fyniſhed my courſe I haue kept the fayth, from hence foorihe then is layed vp for me the croune of righteouſneſſe whyche the Lorde the righteouſe iudge, ſhall geue me at that daye? What coulde be ſpoken more playnelye than thys? For, the Apoſtell doth make mention, both of the worke that he hadde done, and alſo of the rewarde that he loked for at Gods handes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDI.</speaker>
               <p>I would fayne heare, what anſwer ye made vnto them. For this obiection is made many tymes againſte you, of them that be of a contrarye iudgemente and opinion. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRA.</speaker>
               <p>I aunſwered them out of ſaint Auguſtine, where he writeth on this maner:
<q>An non ipſe dedit, vt bonum certamen certares: Sino<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ipſe dedit: quid eſt,<note place="margin">Aug. in. 50. homelis. 14. home.</note> quod alio leco dicis: Plus illis omnibus labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raui. Non autem ego, ſed gratia dei me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum: Ecce iterum dicis: Curſum conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maui. Non et ipſe dedit vt curſum conſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mares?
<pb facs="tcp:12849:61"/> Si non ipſe dedit, vt curſum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mares quid eſt, quod alto loco dicis: no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> volentis ne que currentis, ſed miſerntis eſt dei: Fidem ſeruaui: Seruaſti: Agnoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co, et probo, fateor ſeruaſti. Sed niſedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus cuſtodierit ciuitatem, invanum vis gilat, qui cuſtoditeam.</q>
               </p>
               <p>That is to ſaye: did not he geue, that thou myghteſt fyghte a good fight? If he himſelfe did not geue: What is it, that thou ſayeſt in an other place:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> I laboured more than all they, yet not I, but the grace of God with me? Behold, thou ſaieſt I haue ended my courſe. Did not he alſo geue vnto the, that thou ſhouldeſt finiſhe thy courſe? If be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geue not vnto the,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.</note> that thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt fyniſhe thy courſe, what is it, that thou ſayeſt in an other place: It lyeth no in the willer, nor in the tynner, but in God, that ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wethe mercye? I haue kepte the faith. Haſt thou kepte the faithe? I acknowledge and alowe it, I confeſſe and graunte, thou haſſe kepte the faieth. But accepte the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12849:61"/> Lorde doethe keepe the citye, he watcheth in vayne that doth kepe it. Therefore, thou haſte of hys helpinge hande, and of his mere gyft, that thou haſſe fought a good fighte, that thou haſt finiſhed thy courſe, and kept thy faith.</p>
               <q>De veniam, Apoſtole, propriatua non noui, niſi mala. De veniam Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtole. Dicimus, quia tudo cuiſti Cum er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go deus coronat merita tua, nihil coronat niſi dona ſua.</q>
               <p>Pardone vs, O Apoſtell, ſayeth hee, I knowe nothynge of thyne owne, but euyll. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done vs, O Apoſtell, we ſaye ſo, becauſe thou haſt taughte vs.</p>
               <p>Therefore, when he crouneth thy merites, he crouneth nothinge, but this owne gyftes. By whiche woordes, he doethe ſo attribute the woorke of the Apoſtell, vnto the gyfte and grace of God, that in it there canne not truelye be the meryte of manne, but the grace of God onelye, crouninge his giftes in the Apoſtell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:12849:62"/>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>I myght here aleadge ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other notable autorityes of the aunciente fathers, whiche in all poyntes doe agree with this that ye haue brought in euen now, but for auoydinge of tediouſneſſe. I wyll contente my ſelfe with fewe. <hi>Non dico domino</hi> (ſayth this holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaint Auguſtine:)
<q>Opera manuum mearum ne diſpicias. Exquiſiui dominum, manibus meis, et no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſum deceptus. Sed opera manuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum non co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendo Timeo, enim, ne quum inſpexeris, plura inuenias peccata quam merita. Hocfold diec, hoc rogo, hoc cupio, opera manuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tuarum ne deſpicias. Opus tuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in me vide, non meum. Nam ſi meuin videris da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nas. Si tuum vieris coronas. Nam et quecumque mihi ſunt opera bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na abs te ſunt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>That is: I ſaye not vnto the Lord: deſpiſe not the works of my hands I haue ſoughte the Lord with my handes,<note place="margin">Augu. in pſal. 107.</note> and I was not deceiued. But I do no praiſe or commende the workes of my handes. For, I am affrayed, leaſt when thou lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt vpon them, thou findeſt more
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:12849:62"/> ſinnes than merites. Thys only, I ſaye, this I praye, this I couet. Deſpiſe not the woorkes of thy handes. See thyne owne worke in me, and not myne. For if thou ſeeſt myne, thou doeſt condemne. If thou ſeeſt thine thou crouneſt. For, all the good workes that I haue they are of thee. Here, this holye father doeth plainelye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that as God doeth onelye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of croune in vs that whiche is his owne, ſo be doth condemne al that he findeth to be our owne. And therefore,<note place="margin">Bernardus ſuper canti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca fermo. 61</note> it is not withoute a cauſe that Bernarde doeth ſaye:
<q>Meritum proin de meum miſeratio domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni. Non ſum plane meriti inops, quandiu non fuerit ille inops miſerationum. Quod ſi miſericordie domini multe, multus ego pereque ſum in meritis. Nunquid iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias meas cantabo?<note place="margin">A golden ſayinge of ſaynt Bernard</note> domine meminero iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie tue ſolius. Ipſa, enim, eſt mea.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Nempe factus eſt mihi iuſtitia a deo.</q> That is to ſaye: My merite there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is the mercye of the Lorde. I am not altogether poore or voide, of meryte, as longe as hee is not
<pb facs="tcp:12849:63"/> poore or voyde of mercies.<note place="margin">Workes of ſupere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation, are blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the merits of Chriſt &amp; therfore they ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be called works of derogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> And if the mercies of God be manifolde, truelye I am alſo verye ryche in merites. Shall I ſet foorth myne owne righteouſneſſe? Lord let me remember thy righteouſneſſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For, it is myne: for as much as he is made vnto me of God, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. And in an other place:
<q>Hoc totum hominis meritum, ſi totam ſpem ponat in eum, qui totum hominem ſaluum facit.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This, ſayeth he is the whole me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if he doth put his whole hope in him, that ſaueth the whole man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRA.</speaker>
               <p>If all mounks had ſpoken and writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non other wiſe of the merites of menne, than this holye mounke Bernarde did:<note place="margin">Idem in pſal. <hi>91.</hi>
                  </note> the grace of God, had not bene ſo dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened theſe many hundreth years by vayne extollinge of merites, as it hath bene, nor yet the workes of ſupererogation coulde euer haue bene broughte in, to the greate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation of Chriſtes merites, and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:12849:63"/> of the price of his death and bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheddinge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDI.</speaker>
               <p>They ſhall then frome hencefoorth, be no more called the workes of ſupererogation, but the workes of derogation, ſith that by them the benefitte of that mooſte omniſufficient ſacrifice, that Chriſt offerd once for euer for the redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of mankinde, is ſo blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſlye trodden vnder feete, and the vale we thereof in a maner al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together annichilated, or tourned to nothinge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>That is a fete, name for ſuch vayne and arrogant workes, which doubtles, were brought in of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemy of ſaluation, Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deuil, for to make men to ſwel and be pufte vp againſte the free grace of God, whereby onelye withoute any merites or deſeruings of ours we are all ſaued. But I woulde that menne, puttynge a ſyde all wylfulneſſe woulde ones conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues that the maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtye
<pb facs="tcp:12849:64"/> of God hathe neede of non of vs, nor of any thing that we haue but rather doth geue vs all things abounda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to enioye them.<note place="margin">1. Timo. 6.</note> What good worke then can we do, wher by we maye profitte him in anye thinge,<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.</note> or do him any good?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bonorum meorum non eges.</hi> Thou haſt no neede of my goods, ſayeth Dauid. What merite, I praye you,<note place="margin">God hath no profit by anye good worke, that we can do.</note> can be in that worke, wherof no profit cometh to God? or rather wherof the whole profyt, if there be any, doeth redounde vpon our ſelues? He that is righteous, and doeth good workes, he doeth it not for any commodity, that God ſhall haue therby (for, what commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye can God haue by anye thinge, that we can do?) But for his owne commoditye as he whiche is wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and doeth wickedly, hurtethe him ſelfe,<note place="margin">Similitude</note> and not God. He that hathe the health of his bodye, and doeth by good diet, and moderate excerciſes ſtudye to keepe and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:12849:64"/> it, doethe he therefore, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue anye rewarde at the phiſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons hande? I thinke not. For, he doeth it not for the phiſicions pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyt, but for his owne. After the ſame ſorte, he that by the gyfte of God hathe obtayned the health of his ſoule, and by his grace doethe the thinges, that belonge to the preſeruation of the ſame, ſhall we ſaye, that he doeth deſerue any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde at Goddes handes, becauſe that he is made ſuche by his gyfte, and doeth now through his helpe, ayde and aſſiſtaunce kepe the ſame grace, for his owne profytte, and commoditye, eyther by earneſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, or by vnfaygned loue, or by aſſured hope, or by well doynge, and patience in aduerſitye &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble?<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiecti∣on. </seg>9</label>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDI.</speaker>
               <p>Yet God doeth crowne ſuche.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>God in deede doeth croune in them his giftes, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> whiche are theyr good workes, ſo that all
<pb facs="tcp:12849:65"/> thinges remaine ſafe and ſounde to the glorie of the grace of God. Nowe, where all thinges oughte to be attributed vnto the grace of God, what is lefte for the merites of men? For, where grace is, there is no place left for merite, if we do conſider a right the nature &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of merite. But let our good workes be examined after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtnes of Gods iudgement, who is ſo ignorant,<note place="margin">The im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of oure workes.</note> of mans imperfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that will not acknowledge, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ought rather to feare puniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for the defautes that be in them, than loke for any reward, or boaſte I can not tell of what meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes? Is it for naught, thinke ye, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the holy Prophete doth lykene our righteouſnes to ſo filthy a thinge,<note place="margin">Eſa. 64.</note> that any man will abhorre to loke on it? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>10</label>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDI.</speaker>
               <p>But this, ſaye they ought to be vnderſtanded of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſnes of the fleſh, I mean of the man, that is not yet iuſtified.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:12849:65"/>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>Sainct Auguſtin in his bokes of confeſſions, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> doeth crye out, that it ought to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded of the righteouſneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſtians, I meane, of thoſe that he alredy graffed in Chriſt, where he ſayeth:
<q>Nae vniuerſae iuſtitie noſtre,<note place="margin">Augu. li. 9. confeſſionu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </note> ſi remota miſercordia iudicetur.</q>
               </p>
               <p>That is: Wo be to all our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, if it be iudged, mercy bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge taken awaye, or ſet aſyde.</p>
               <p>What manner of merite is that, whiche can not abyde the cenſure of Gods iudgement, nor be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from condemnation, but tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough mercy onely? withoute all doubt, better it is for vs to confeſſe our ſinnes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Publicane,<note place="margin">Aug. de. S. virg. ca. 42.</note> than to glorie, boaſt &amp; bragge of our me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rites w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Phariſee. Such are our merites, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion, &amp; acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging of our ſinnes, ought to be preferred before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bring of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Bernard doeth not in this poynte diſagree from ſaincte Auguſtine. For, theſe are his woordes.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12849:66"/>Sed quid poteſt eſſe o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nis iuſtitia noſtra coram deo? None iuxta prophetam, velut pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nus menſtruate reputabitur,<note place="margin">Bernardus in ſermone pefeſto om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium ſancto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rum. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> et ſi di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtricte iudicetur, intuſta inuenietur omnis iuſtitia noſtra et minus habens? Quid ergo depeccatis erit, quando <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem per ſe poterit reſpondere iuſtitia? Propterea enixe cum propheta clamantes non intres in iudicium cum ſeruo tuo, o domine: nam non iuſtificabitur in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectu tuo omnis viuens, tota humilitate, ad miſericordiam recurtamus, que fola poteſt ſaluare animas noſtras.</q>
               <p>That is to ſaye: But what can al our righteouſnes be before god? Shall it not, according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phette,<note place="margin">Eſa. 64.</note> be coumpted as a fylthye bloudi cloute? And if it be ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye iudged, ſhal not al oure righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe bee ſounde vnryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe, and hauynge leſſe, than it oughte to haue? What ſhall then become of our ſyns, if our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 143.</note> canne not aunſwer by it ſelfe? Therefore cryinge earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye wyth the prophete: Enter not in to iudgemente, o Lorde, wyth thy ſeruaunte, for, in thy ſyght no man liuinge ſhall be iuſtifyed, let vs with al humility, haue oure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:12849:66"/> vnto mercye, whiche alone is able to ſaue our ſoules. But go to, al theſe golde ſayings being lai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed a ſide, let vs compare the ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable glorye of lyfe euerlaſtinge,<note place="margin">The ineſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mable glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye of life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting doth cut of all merites.</note> and of endeleſſe felicitye, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye with oure good works, be they neuer ſo glorious and exelent, but alſo with the afflictions, troubles perſecutions and aduerſities, that we do here ſuffer for Chriſts ſake, what ſhall we finde in them, that is able too counterpeaſe the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable ioyes that are laied vp for the electe and choſen of God? For, thus ſayeth ſainte Paule:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> I coumpt, that the afflictions of this preſente tyme, are not worthye of the glorye, whiche ſhall be ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vnto vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRA.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe one thing doe I learne by that whiche hathe bene ſpoken, of the merites of our owne workes. And that is this: Sith that God in geuing vs vnto life euerlaſting, doeth not reſpect
<pb facs="tcp:12849:67"/> or regard the dignitie of our good workes: howe can the doctrine of them ſtande, which do appoint de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of ioye and felicitie in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> affirming that we ſhal there excel one an other in glorye? This is moſt ſure that we obtayn heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly felicitye by the mere mercy of god. And therefore, this diuerſitye or difference of rewards muſt depend or hange of the mercy of God, and not of oure owne workes.<note place="margin">Wherup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they grounde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues that do appoynte diuerſity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of glorye in the life to come.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>We ſee that they whiche mayntaine the contrarye, do ground them ſelues vpon this, that we do by oure good workes, deſerue life euerlaſtinge, as they ſaye, <hi>ex condigno,</hi> or accordingely. Which thing, if we wold graunt, then withoute all controuerſye, God ſhoulde ſeeme vnrighteouſe, if he ſhoulde not geue greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes to thoſe, that haue, labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, merited and deſerued more than the other. But let vs come to the ſcriptures.<note place="margin">Math. 20.</note> Fyrſte, a penye
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:12849:67"/> is equaly geuen to thoſe, that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured in the vineyarde, although ſome of them, came at thre of the clocke, ſome at nyne, and ſome at eleuen, and when they began to murmure, the father of the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houlde ſtopped their mouthes ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge, that he did iuſtelye. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye the Apoſtell affyrmeth,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> that God ſhall be all in all. And when our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt ſpeaketh of the rewarde of the righteouſe. The righteouſe ſayeth he, ſhall ſhyne as the ſunne in the ſighte of God.<note place="margin">Mat. 13.</note> But there is no greater lyghte, than the light of the ſunne: and no manne ſhall enter in to the kingdome of heauen, excepte he be righteous. They ſhal then haue al the light or brightneſſe of the ſun, that is lyke or equall glorye. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoning with the Saducees of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, doth ſay,<note place="margin">Luc. 20.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhalbe like vnto the Au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gels, neither goeth he any farther or appointeth any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees.
<pb facs="tcp:12849:68"/> Beſides this, that there be diuers and ſondrye differences betwixte the Sayntes here in this life, that cometh by the reaſon of the fleſhe, that they carye aboute, and the more or leſſe that they be addicted vnto it, the more or leſſe they doe profytte in the regeneration: but when in the lande of the liuinge, all the corruption of our fleſh ſhal be taken awaye, we ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte, neyther ſhall there be anye cauſe, whye the one ſhall be more letted than the other fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge of the heauenly glorye.<note place="margin">Mat. 19.</note> Did not alſo our ſauioure Ieſus Chriſt promyſſe vnto his Apoſtels, that they ſhoulde ſet vpon .xii. ſeates, and iudge the .xii. tribes of Iſrael? And did not Paule make the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.</note> and with them all the faythfull beleuers, partakers of this rewarde, when he ſayeth: do ye not knowe, that the ſaynts ſhal iudge both the world, and alſo the Aungels? Theſe places do playn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:12849:68"/> take awaye all diuerſityes of rewardes or degrees in glorye. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiecti∣on. </seg>11</label>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>Whye then doeth the Apoſtel ſay: There is an other glory of the ſun,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> &amp; an other glorye of the moone, and an other glorye of the ſtarres. For, one ſtarre dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth from an other ſtarre in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, ſo alſo is the reſurrection of the deade. Doeth not he ſhew here a diuerſitye of rewardes, and that after the bleſſed reſurrection ſome ſhall be more gloryous than the other?<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>Ye go cleane from the meaning of the Apoſtel. For, there he doeth proue, that as the ſunne and the moone beinge of one ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce do differ in dignitye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo in the reſurrection, oure bodyes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe they ſhall be the ſame in ſubſtaunce, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be now, yet ſhal they haue more excelent qualityes than they haue nowe at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente. And that the like muſte be vnderſtanded of the compariſon of
<pb facs="tcp:12849:69"/> the ſtarres, it is euident and plain by the concluſion that Paule doth inferre or bringe in ſayinge: The bodye is ſowen in corruption, and is rayſed in incorruption, it is ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen in diſhonour and is rayſed in glorye, it is ſowen in weakeneſſe, and is rayſed in power. Wherby it doeth moſte playnlye appeare, that this diuerſitye oughte onelye to be taken for the diuerſitye, that is betwixte the bodye, whiche we ſhal put of at our death, &amp; the body that ſhall be reſtored agayne, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can anye thinge be here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded of anye difference or dyuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, that ſhall be betwixt the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or glorifyed bodyes.<note place="margin">Luc. 20.</note> Chriſte doeth onelye ſpeake generallye of this thinge, when he ſayeth, that we ſhall all be lyke vnto the Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.<note place="margin">Phi. 3.</note> Agayne, the holye Apoſtell ſayeth, that when oure ſauioure ſhall come downe frome heauen, he wyll chaunge and tranſforme oure vyle bodyes, and make them
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:12849:69"/> lyke vnto his glorious body, what diuerſitye of glorye (I praye you) can there be, when all our bodyes ſhall be made like vnto the glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bodye of Chriſt. How be it, I wil not be to preciſe in this matter leaſt I ſhoulde ſeeme too affyrme anye thynge raſhely.<note place="margin">To attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute anye parte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauenly felicity &amp; glory, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rits of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is to be iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry of the grace of God.</note> Onelye this wyll I warne the Godlye of, that although they do with ſome of the fathers graunte that there be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of glory in the lyfe to come, yet let them beware and take hede that they doe in no wyſe attribute the ſame vnto the merites, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruinges of menne. For, that wer to do to muche iniurye and wrong vntoo the glorye of the grace of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>Doeth not Paule wryte, that it ſhall be rendred vnto euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according vnto his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes? Again theſe,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> I am ſure are his words: we muſt al appear before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeat of Chriſt,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eueri ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs which are don <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiecti∣on. </seg>12</label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12849:70"/> in his bodye, accordinge to that he hath done, whether it be good or euyll. Theſe wordes do playn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teſtifye, that euerye manne ſhall receaue a rewarde accordinge to his labour. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALE.</speaker>
               <p>We do gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallye vnderſtand this of the elect and reprobate, and of their glory and dampnation. So doeth Paull expounde it, in the Epiſtell to the Romayns.<note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> And Chriſt him ſelfe, in the ſentence that he ſhall geue at his laſt iudgemente, doeth ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientlye declare, what this ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture meanethe: when he callethe them that be at his right hande to his kyngedome, and ſendeth thoſe that be at his lefte in to the fyer e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting that is prepared for the deuyll and his Aungelles. Nowe, as touching the works of the elect ye haue learned alredy, that when God rewardeth them he crouneth in them his owne giftes.<note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> But as for the reprobate, thei do according
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:12849:70"/> ſo the frutes of their wycked and vnbeleuinge hartes, receaue eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall dampnation, which is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of vnbelief. Non other thing can we learne of thoſe places that ye haue aleadged.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>I am ſure ye wyll not denye, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>13</label> but that theſe be Daniels wordes.</p>
               <q>Qui alios docent, erunt vt ſplendor fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mamenti,<note place="margin">Dau. 12.</note> quique ad iuſtitiam alios in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrunt, vt ſtelle fulgebunt.</q>
               <p>That is too ſaye: They that teache other, ſhal be as the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the firmamente, and they that inſtructe other vnto righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, ſhal ſhyne as the ſtarres. Looke what difference there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the brightenes of the firma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente, and the brightneſſe of the ſtarres, the ſame ſhall be euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixte thoſe that teache. For, they, that by their dilgente tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge ſhal wynne and bring ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye to righteouſeneſſe ſhall ſhyne as the brighteneſſe of ſtarres, the
<pb facs="tcp:12849:71"/> other that haue leſſe laboured in the lordes vineyarde ſhyninge on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye as the bryghteneſſe of the fyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mamente. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>As touchinge Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels words where he ſayeth: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye that ſleepe in the duſte of the earthe ſhall awake,<note place="margin">Tge expo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſition of Daniels wordes.</note> ſome to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtinge life, and ſome to ſhame and perpetual contempt. And they that teach, ſhal ſhine as the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the firmament, and thei that bringe many to righteouſnes, ſhal ſhine as the ſtarres for euer &amp; euer: Do make lytle or nothing for this matter. For (as it hapeneth many times in the ſcriptures) in one pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riodus or ſentence, the ſame ſelfe thynges are repeted the ſeconde time, which wer ſpoken firſt. The difference that ſemethe here to be aſſigned or appoynted, is of the fir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mamente and of the ſtarres. But ſyth that they that teache, and thei that inſtructe and bringe other too righteouſeneſſe, be all one, and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:12849:71"/> are conteyned vnder one degree: after the verye iudgemente of the aduerſaryes, diuers rewardes are not due vnto them, ſyth that they laboured both in one thing. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is moſt manifeſt and playn, that the ſame is repeted agayne, which was already ſpoken before, but more playnlye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>AL.</speaker>
               <p>But why doeth Daniell make mention of the miniſters or teachers, rather than of the reſte? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe that aboue all other, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> they be ſubiecte to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quution and trouble, and therfore they haue moſt nede of coumforte, that they may with a good corage take vpon them, this moſte pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and troubleſome office, and perſeuere in it to the ende. But it can not be proued therby, that like rewardes are not promiſſed vnto the other, ſith that oure ſauioure Ieſus Chriſte doeth expreſſely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme,<note place="margin">Math. 13.</note> that the righteous ſhal ſhine as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſunne in the kingdom of god.
<pb facs="tcp:12849:72"/> Agayn, that ſome wynne or bring more than ſome, vnto righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note place="margin">Note.</note> that oughte not to be attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the connynge, induſtrye or laboure of men, but vnto him, that by openinge the hearts of the hearers, doeth geue the encreaſe, the Apoſtell hym ſelfe ſayinge. Neyther he that planteth, nor he that watreth is any thyng but the Lorde,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.</note> whyche geuethe the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiecti∣on. </seg>14</label> Yet Ierome expoundinge this place, ſayeth: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wheras many do aſke, whether the godly vnlearned,<note place="margin">Hier. in. 12. ca. Dani.</note> and the godly learned ſhall haue the lyke glory. aunſwer may be made vnto them after the tranſlation of Theodotio that the one ſhall be as the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente and the other as the ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> But no ſuch thinge, canne be gathered of the tranſlation, whiche is after the Hebrewe. For, in it we haue
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:12849:72"/> playnlye theſe wordes:
<q>Porro doctores ſplendebunt vt ſplendor firmamenti: et qui multos ad iuſtitiam ad ducunt, vt ſtellae ſepiternis temporibus.</q> Which we may engliſh after this maner: and the teachers ſhal ſhine as the fyrmamente, and they that bringe manye to righteouſeneſſe, ſhall ſhyne as the ſtarres worldes without ende. Who doeth not ſee, that all one thynge is meante in bothe cloſes, ſauinge that in the laſte, the mattyer is made more playne?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>Ye wyll graunt, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>15</label> I am ſure, that there is a diuerſity in the puniſhementes of the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, it foloweth then that there is alſo a diuerſitye in the rewardes of the electe and choſen. And that the puniſhments of the reprobate, be not all one, it maye eaſelye be proued by the woordes of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyour Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Math. 11.</note> where he ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that it ſhalbe eaſier at the day of iudgemente for them of Tyre
<pb facs="tcp:12849:73"/> and Sydonne, than for them of Corozam and Bethſaida, and for them of Sodome and Gomorre, than for them of Capernaum.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> The argumentes that be made a contrarys, do not alwaies neceſſarily conclude. For why? This kinde of argument do manye tymes deceyue. As if one ſhoulde ſaye or reaſonne after this ſorte: A man can kyll hym ſelfe, ergo he can make him ſelf to lyue. Manye other inſtaunces myghte I bringe, but for ſhorteneſſe ſake, I do paſſe them ouer.<note place="margin">Whither is a diuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſity in the puniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the repro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bate and non in the rewardes of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecte and choſen.</note> Well go to: I graunte that there is adiuerſity in the puniſhementes of the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate. And why? Becauſe, that they do by theyr vnbeliefe and frutes of the ſame, deſerue thoſe puniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of hell fyer: but it can not be truly ſayed, that the electe and choſen doe by theyr workes merit or deſerue the endeleſſe ioye and felicitye of heauen. Therfore there is a verye vnlyke reaſon in theeſe
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:12849:73"/> contraryes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>What meaneth Chriſte, when he ſayeth: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>16</label> There be manye manſions in my fathers houſe?<note place="margin">Ioa. 14.</note> Doeth not he therby ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye a difference or diuerſitye of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALE.</speaker>
               <p>Yf Chriſte had ſayed:<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> There be diuers dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge places in my fathers houſe: youre ſayinge myghte haue ſome coloure. But he ſayed: There be manye dwellynge places<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of no diuerſitye at all canne be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, but rather, that there is rowme ynoughe for all hys electe and choſen bee they neuer ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye. For,<note place="margin">Ioa. 14.</note> we muſt not groſſelye ymagyne that there bee ſondrye chambers or parloures in heauen, ſome beynge more gloryous than ſome, but that wher ſo euer Chriſt oure headde ſhal be, there we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be alſo wyth him. As he him ſelfe doeth teſtify ſayinge:</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12849:74"/>
               <p>I wyll come agayne, and receaue you vnto my ſelfe, that where I am, there maye ye be alſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>17</label> I remember, that ye ſayed afore that accordinge to oure ſauioure Ieſus Chriſtes wordes, we ſhal be like vnto Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. But ye can not deny, but that ther be diuers orders and degrees, amonge them. For, ſome are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Archangels,<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 1.</note> ſome, Thrones, ſome Dominions, Principalities, &amp; powers. Syth then that we ſhal be lyke aungels, and among them, there be ſuch diuers orders and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees: it can none other wyſe be gathered, but that there ſhall be a diuerſitye or difference of glorye amonge the ſayntes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> As touchinge Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles, the ſcripture doeth nowe confeſſe, that they haue diuers or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, principalityes, dominions and powers amonge them ſelues, becauſe, that as long as we do liue in this wicked worlde and vale of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:12849:74"/> miſerye, they are appoynted to be miniſters and helpers vnto vs,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.</note> as we reade in the Epiſtell to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes. Yea they be alſo appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted too be as it were rulers ouer common wealles, and kingdoms,<note place="margin">Dan. 10.</note> as Daniell doeth teſtifye, they are alſo kepers of men, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of God to wayte vppon them,<note place="margin">Pſal. 91.</note> whereof it cometh, that our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus Chriſt doeth ſaye of the children,<note place="margin">Math. 18.</note> that their Aungels doe alwayes ſee the face of their father that is in heauen. But when in the kingdome of Chriſt,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> all things ſhall be pacifyed,<note place="margin">The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> now is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge Aungels ſhal ceaſſe at the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</note> theſe ſeruices or miniſteries, as vnneceſſarye and ſuperflue ſhall be abolyſhed. Read for that, the .xv. chapter of the firſt Epiſtell to the Corinthians. If ſo be then that the diuerſitye that is nowe amonge Aungels by reaſon of the ſondrye offices and miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that they be appoynted vnto, for the preſeruation of the electe, and choſen, ſhall ceaſſe, at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection
<pb facs="tcp:12849:75"/> of all fleſh, what ſhould we dreame of anye dyfference or diuerſitye, that ſhoulde be amonge vs then, ſyth that Chriſt dyd with ſo playne wordes affirme, that we ſhall then be like Aungels?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiecti∣on. </seg>18</label> I wyll not yet geue ouer. Who ſo euer (ſayeth Chriſt) ſhall obſerue,<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> and teache the commaundementes, the ſame ſhall be called greate in the kinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen.<note place="margin">Mat. 13.</note> He ſayth beſides, that the corne that dyd falle in too good grounde, did bringe foorthe frute,<note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> ſome an hundreth folde, ſome ſyxty folde, and ſome thyrty folde. And in the parable of the talents, we reade, that the ſeruaunts were recompenſed accordinge,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 9.</note> to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitye of the gaynes. Agayne, are not theſe Pauls woordes: He that ſoweth ſparingly ſhal reape,<note place="margin">Math. 20.</note> alſo ſparynglye, and he that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth liberallye ſhal reape alſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berallye? Chriſt ſayed likewyſe to his diſciples: he that wyll be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:12849:75"/> amonge you, let him be leaſt. Theſe places, I trowe, do ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientelye teache,<note place="margin">Luc. 22.</note> that there ſhall be a diuerſitye, after the glorify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the children of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>To the firſt we doo aunſwer,<note place="margin">Aunſwer to the .5. of Math.</note> that by the kingdome of heauen, the churche of God, is vnderſtanded wher thei oughte to be in moſte eſtimation, that both teache ſyncerely, and do by their lyfe, and conuerſation, expreſſe that, which they do teach. And alſo in eccleſiaſtycall electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they oughte to be preferred before the other, and they to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected and put backe, that do both breake the commaundementes, and teache other alſo to doo ſo.</p>
               <p>Onleſſe, ye wyl ſay, that they that lyue wyckedlye, and teache other both by theyr woordes and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple too tranſgreſſe the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes of God, ſhall enioye e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall felicitye, whiche were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte all reaſon.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12849:76"/>
               <p>And as for the parable of the ſede, whereof parte did fall in to good grounde:<note place="margin">Aunſwer to the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the ſede. Mat. 13.</note> anye manne can eaſelye perceaue, that it pertayneth vnto the ſtate of this prſente life, and that therby it is ſignified that the worde of God doethe not brynge foorth frute in lyke, in al the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye.<note place="margin">To the parable of the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentes. Mat. 25.</note> Likewyſe the parable of the talentes, doeth certifye vs, that they, that vſe well the gyftes of God, in them the grace of god ſhal daylye encreaſe, yea they ſhall be made worthye too be rulers ouer muche, that is to ſaye, euery daye they ſhal be made more able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue ſpirituall gyftes. Neyther canne the place,<note place="margin">To the place of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeconde to the Co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. 2. Cor. 9.</note> that ye haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged oute of the ſeconde too the Corinthians be otherwyſe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded. For, we do commonlye ſee that they that be Godly liberal in geuinge of almes, do not onely abounde in ſpirituall gyftes, but haue alſo by the bleſſynge of God, theyr temporall rycheſſe wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:12849:76"/> encreaſed and augmented, that they maye the better exerciſe theyr Godlye liberalitye towardes the poore members of our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt. Which is according to the ſayinge of the wyſe manne,<note place="margin">Proue. 3.</note> where he ſaieth: Honour the Lord with thy rycheſſe (but how canne we honoure the Lorde wyth oure rycheſſe, but by refreſhinge his ſon Ieſus Chriſte in hys lymmes?) ſo ſhall thy barnes be fylled with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundaunce, and thy wynne preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſhall burſte with newe wyne. And where Chriſt ſayeth to his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtelles:<note place="margin">To the place of the .22. of Luc.</note> he that wyll be greateſt amonge you, let him be leaſte, the ſame can not be applied, but to the churche of God, where they ought too be coumpted greateſt, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge endued with moſte excellente gyftes, and beſtowinge the ſame to the edifying of the faythfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, to behaue them ſelues moſt humblye. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiecti∣on. </seg>19</label>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>I fynd this writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb facs="tcp:12849:77"/> in the Apocalipſe or reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Iohn:<note place="margin">Apoca. 14.</note> I hearde a voyce from heauen, as the ſound of many wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and as the ſounde of a great thunder, I harde the voyce of har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, harpinge vpon theyr harps. And they ſonge, as it were a new ſonge before the throne, and before the .iiii. beaſtes, and the ealders, and no man can learne that ſong, but the hundreth fortye and foure thouſande, which were boughte frome the earthe. Theſe are they, whych are not defyled wyth wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men:</p>
               <p>For, they are virgines, theſe folowe the lambe, whether ſoeuer he goeth. Here we ſee, that onely thoſe hundreth fortye and foure thouſande, whiche afterwardes he calleth virgines, coulde ſynge the newe ſounge, and folowe the lambe, whether ſo euer he goeth. whereby it doeth appeare, that they haue a preeminence aboue all the reſt, and that they doo alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celle
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:12849:77"/> other in glory.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALE.</speaker>
               <p>By this finit number of an hundreth forty and foure thouſande, is vnderſtanded, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> the infynitte number of the electe and choſen of God,<note place="margin">Who thei be that can ſinge the new ſonge.</note> which alone canne ſynge the new ſounge.</p>
               <p>For, the elect only canne praiſe and laude God, neyther canne any ſay, that Ieſus is the Lord, but by the holy ghoſt, whereof all the reprobate are voyd.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And it is ſayed that they are vyrgines,<note place="margin">Why the true elect are called virgines. Heb. 13.</note> and haue not defyled them ſelues wyth women, not becauſe that they haue lyued oute of holye wedlocke, whiche, as the Apoſtell ſayethe, is honourable amonge all menne, but becauſe that the churche,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> and fayethfull congregation, hathe bene by the Apoſtelles, and nowe is by theyr doctryn prepared for one huſband, and preſented as a pure virgine to Chriſt.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12849:78"/>
               <p>Thei are therfore called virgines, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> after they were brought to Chriſte, and ſanctifyed through faythe in his bloude, and alſo wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and iuſtified, they neuer defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them ſelues with that ſtraunge woman,<note place="margin">Prou. 4.</note> which the wiſe man doth ſpeake of, that is to ſay, with any ſtraunge doctrine of ſtinkinge ydo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrye, and of other ſuperſtitious worſhippings and ſeruices of god, but haue kepte their myndes pure and chaſte virgynes vnto Chriſte theyr huſbande vnto whome they were maryed wyth a ſincere and pure fayth.<note place="margin">What it is to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the lambe whether ſo euer he goeth.</note> Theeſe be they that folowe the lambe whether ſo euer he goeth. For, as whiles they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde here in the worlde, Chriſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is their treaſure, theyr ioye, and coumforte: in him onely they put theyr confidence, and truſte: and whether ſoeuer he calleth them by his doctrine and example, they be be alwayes readye to folowe him, though it be to a moſt cruell death,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:12849:78"/> to glorye him with all: ſo in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worlde, they be neuer ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from him. For, where ſoeuer Chriſte is,<note place="margin">Ioa. 12.</note> there ſhall his miniſter or ſeruaunte be alſo. But all the elect and choſen of god, are Chriſts miniſters and ſeruaunts, therfore where ſo euer he is, there ſhal thei be alſo. Nowe maye ye perceaue, how little this place of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, can helpe them, that maintayn this diuerſitye of rewardes in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>AL.</speaker>
               <p>Are not all the fathers, I <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiecti∣on. </seg>20</label> praye you, of this opinion? Again, wyll not men be made more ſlacke to doe good woorkes, if they once vnderſtande, that there ſhall be no diuerſitye, or difference of rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des in the lyfe to come.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>As for the fathers we do confeſſe and graunt, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue appoynted ſuche diuerſity or diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of rewards. But herein lieth the whole controuerſye, whether this can be proued by the infallible
<pb facs="tcp:12849:79"/> teſtimonyes and autorytyes of the ſcriptures or not. Agayn, they do not ſpeake of it, all after one ſorte. For, Hierome, when in his Epiſtels he did commend we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowhode,<note place="margin">Ierome.</note> and was come to that poynte, that he muſt needes make a comparyſon, betwixte the we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe and the virgyne, he doeth playnelye ſaye, that he wyll not gladlye appoynte any diuerſity or difference betwyxt the Sayntes: and yet in other places, be wyll ſeme to be an earneſt mainetainer of theſe differences. And whereas ye ſaye, that men by this doctrine are made more remyſſe, negly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente, and ſlacke to do good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, I haue aunſwered you alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, that the electe and choſen of God, be wont at all tymes, to doo good workes for the loue that they beare to God, and to theyr neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure, and for to ſhewe theyr o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedyence towardes the ſacredde word and holy commaundements
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:12849:79"/> of theyr heauenly father, without anye reſpecte of recompence or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, and that they, that doe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe are but mercenaries and hyrelyngs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>And ſhall the bleſſed virgyne Mary, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion </seg>
                  </label> the mother of oure ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt with the Apoſtels and martyres, be in no higher glorye than the reſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>That I leaue to the vnſercheable iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of God, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> who (if it had ben neceſſary for our ſaluation) would haue certified vs of it in his word. But in the mean ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this ought to be learned of all men,<note place="margin">If any do excell o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in glory af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this lif it is not by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on of theyr merites.</note> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the lyfe to come any do excell other in glori, it is not by reaſon of their workes merites or deſeruinges, but the ſame doth altogether come of the mere mercye, grace and goodneſſe of God, who doth moſt lyberallye crowne in them hys owne gyftes, as it hath ben ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientlye proued before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:12849:80"/>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>This haue I learned of our talke and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication. Fyrſt that we are iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed freely,<note place="margin">The epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logus or concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> that is to ſaye, deliuered from ſynne, frome eternall damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and euerlaſtinge death, and pronounced righteouſe, before the iudgement ſeate of almighty god, throughe fayth onelye in our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure Ieſus Chriſte, withoute any merites, or deſeruinges goynge before, and that as all the workes that we do, afore we be iuſtified, I meane, afore we bee graffed in Chriſte through faieth in him, and made liuely members of his body, are nothinge elles in the ſighte of God but ſynnes:<note place="margin">Ioa. 15.</note> ſo after we be once iuſtifyed, and made through fayth braunches of that true vine, we muſt not remayne bareine and vnfrutefull trees, but wee muſte bringe foorthe the frutes of oure fayeth,<note place="margin">Ephe 2.</note> we muſte abounde, and as it were, flowe in all kinde of good workes, that God hathe prepared
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:12849:80"/> for vs to walke in, whereby wyll workes that is works, of mannes inuention, hauing no ſure ground or fundation, nor yet any promiſe in Goddes booke, are cleane ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen. Secondly, it hath bene declared, that not all they, that do thoſe works, which in them ſelues are good,<note place="margin">Three ſortes of people which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe they do good wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes do not deſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prayſe of weldoing</note> doo by and by deſerue the prayſe and commendation of good worokes or of well doynge, for as muche, as they do them, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for to be glorifyed of men, or for hope of rewarde, or for feare of eternall punyſhement, and not for the loue only that thei beare to god and to theyr neyghboure, or for to ſhewe theyr obedience towardes Goddes holye comaundementes. Where throughe, occaſion was geuen, to ſhewe the cauſes, that ſhould moue vs to do good works, althoughe there were no hope at all of rewarde: and alſo the cauſes whye the workes of thoſe that be graffed in Chriſte by fayeth (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:12849:81"/> in them ſelues they be moſt vnperfect) do pleaſe God &amp; are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable in hys ſyghte. Afterwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, ye ſpake of merits, prouinge moſte ſtronglye, that although we were able to do what ſo euer God hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded vs, yet we ought to coumpte oure ſelues vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruauntes, and that we haue done but our duetye, and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wythſtandynge, that oure good workes, whiche beinge members of Chriſte, we doe accordinge to the preſcripte and rule of Goddes worde, ſhall be crowned and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, not for their owne digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye and worthyneſſe, or for anye perfection that is in them, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that the perfecte obedyence of Chriſte, ſhall be imputed vnto vs for our owne, and thereby all thinges, that be wantinge and lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge in vs, moſte aboundantlye ſupplied, by reaſon of the felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe, that wee haue throughe fayeth in the only begotten ſonne
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:12849:81"/> df God: And alſo becauſe of the promiſſes, wherby God is become debtoure vnto vs. Laſte of all, ye haue proued by manyfeſt textes of the ſcriptures, and by anſwering all obiections, that could be made to the contrarye, that we ſhall be al one, and receyue al one reward, in the reſurrection of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe, and if there ſhall be any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of glorye (whiche thinge can not well be proued by the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res) that oughte in no wyſe too be attributed vnto the merittes, and deſeruinges of men, but to the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mercy, goodneſſe, and grace of God, declared vnto vs in his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt and taken hold vpon by faith in the merits of his death, paſſion, and bloud ſhedding.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>This in dede is the ſumme of our talke, that we haue hadde at this preſente. Ye haue well remembred the pighte of the whole matter. Whyche is a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of a pregnaunte wytte, and
<pb facs="tcp:12849:82"/> good memorye. God of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, vouchafe to encreaſe in you theſe his excelente giftes, and too heape you wyth all heauenly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinges, that ye maye by embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinge the true religion, by aduaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cinge and fartheringe of it, be an exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple vnto al the whole world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDI.</speaker>
               <p>God of hys mercye voucheſafe to graunt it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPELVS.</speaker>
               <p>AMEN, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:12849:82"/>
            <head>¶<hi>HERE BEGIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth</hi> a Table, whereby ye maye fynde ſpedelye, all the principall matters contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Theiſtes what they are. folio. 2.</item>
               <item>A principall note to whome the Apoſtell did write. fo. 8.</item>
               <item>Althoughe we haue not in the ſcriptures this word ſola, only or alone, yet haue we many wordes that be of lyke force. fo. 13.</item>
               <item>An euaſion of the enemies. fo. 24</item>
               <item>A golden ſayinge of ſaynte Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narde. fo. 55</item>
               <item>Abraham was iuſtified. 30. yeares afore the offeringe of his ſonne I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac. foli. 7.</item>
               <item>Aunſwer to the 5. of Math. fo. 68.</item>
               <item>Aunſwer to the parable of the ſede folio. eodem.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:12849:83"/>
               <item>Chriſt onely hathe ſatiſfied to the iuſtice of God. fo. 6.</item>
               <item>Chriſte is a ſufficiente expoſitour. of his owne wordes. fo. 27</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E</head>
               <item>Euyl works do declare the malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes of oure hartes. fo. 45.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F.</head>
               <item>From whence this worde iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care to iuſtifye hath bene borowed and what it ſignifyeth. fo. 4.</item>
               <item>Faith is not taken of the Apoſtels in one ſignification fo. 9.</item>
               <item>Gardiners obiection agaynſt doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor Barnes. fo. 28.</item>
               <item>Good intentes. fo. 37.</item>
               <item>God hathe no profit by anye good worke that we can do fo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 506.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H.</head>
               <item>Howe the ſcriptures are aleaged by the enemies of the truth. fo. 27</item>
               <item>Howe oure good intentes whiche haue no waraunt in Gods woorde are rewarded. fo. 39</item>
               <item>How earneſtlye the cauſes aboue reherſed oughte to moue vs to doe good woorkes. fo. 49.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:12849:83"/>
               <head>I</head>
               <item>Iuſtification is taken awaye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together frome the lawe of Moſes and attributed vnto fayth fo. 11.</item>
               <item>If it be an hereſy to ſay that fayth only iuſtifieth all the auncient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers be heritikes. fo. 21.</item>
               <item>If any do excell other in glorye af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this lyfe, it is not be reaſon of theyr merites fo. 72.</item>
               <item>Iuſtification wherby we are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from ſinne is neceſſarye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs as longe as we liue. fo. 25.</item>
               <item>In doynge of good woorkes we muſte folow the example of Chriſt folio. 44.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M.</head>
               <item>Mercenaries &amp; hierlinges. fo. 43.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O.</head>
               <item>One text muſt geue place to many folio. 10.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P.</head>
               <item>Peace of conſcience doeth exclude wauering or doubtfulnes of mind folio. 32.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S.</head>
               <item>Saule ſtandethe in defence of hys
<pb facs="tcp:12849:84"/> diſobedience. folio. 39.</item>
               <item>Similitude. fo. 56.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T.</head>
               <item>The maliciouſnes of the enemies of the truthe. fol. 1.</item>
               <item>The Popes kingdome is a kinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of lyes. folio. 4.</item>
               <item>They that are iuſtified by workes are able or muſt be be able to aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere fullye to the iuſtice of God. folio. 5.</item>
               <item>The offeringe of Iſaac is a teſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monye of the fayth and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Abraham. fol. 8.</item>
               <item>This word to iuſtify is otherwiſe taken of Paul then of Iames. fo. 9.</item>
               <item>To attribute iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto any merites goyng before is a deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the grace of God. fo. 12.</item>
               <item>The enemies of the truth are to be likened to the Arians. fol. 15.</item>
               <item>The purpoſe of God doeth exclude all merites and deſeruinges from the iuſtification of man. fo. 17</item>
               <item>The fathers were to be blamed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do affyrme fayth onely to iuſtify if
<pb facs="tcp:12849:84"/> that doctrine wer not true. fo. 24</item>
               <item>The hiſtory of Cornelius fo. 30</item>
               <item>The frutes of iuſtification. fo. 31</item>
               <item>The firſte frute of iuſtifycation. folio. eodem.</item>
               <item>The 2. frute of iuſtification. fo. 32.</item>
               <item>The certaynety of Gods promiſe. folio. 33.</item>
               <item>The .4 frute of iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. fo. eode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </item>
               <item>The .5. frute of iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. fo. eode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </item>
               <item>The common doctrin of preachers touching good works. fol. 35.</item>
               <item>The deuil did peruerte the ende of our creation which Chriſt reſtored agayne. fo. eodem</item>
               <item>The works of the papiſtes. fo. 36</item>
               <item>They that are enemies of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes good workes are enemies of ſynne, and of moſt deteſtable abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. fo. 37.</item>
               <item>Terrible and dreadefull hiſtories. folio. 38.</item>
               <item>The order that god had appointed touchinge the Arke. fo. 39.</item>
               <item>The hiſtorye of Saul. fol. 40</item>
               <item>The vntrue reporte of the papiſts
<pb facs="tcp:12849:85"/> folio. 43.</item>
               <item>They y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worke for feare are lewde ſeruauntes. fol. 44.</item>
               <item>The cauſes whye our good works do pleaſe God fo. 47.</item>
               <item>The cauſes why we canne by our good workes merit no part of our ſaluation fo. 51.</item>
               <item>The imperfection of our workes. folio. 57.</item>
               <item>The ineſtimable glorye of lyfe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtynge doeth cutte awaye all merites fo. 59.</item>
               <item>To attribute any parte of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly felicitye and glorye vnto the merits, of men it is to be iniurious vnto the glory of the grace of God folio. 62.</item>
               <item>The expoſition of Daniels words folio. 63.</item>
               <item>The diuerſity that now is among Aungels ſhal ceaſſe at the generall reſurrection of the righteous. fo. 67</item>
               <item>To the parable of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> talents fo. eode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </item>
               <item>To y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place of the .2 to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cor. fo. eo.</item>
               <item>To the place of the .22 of Luc fo. 99</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:12849:85"/>
               <item>The epilogus or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion. fo. eod.</item>
               <item>Three ſortes of people althoughe thei do good works do not deſerue the praiſe of wel doinge fo. 73</item>
               <item>The perfecte obedience of Chriſte is imputed vnto vs. foli. 73.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V.</head>
               <item>Vzah ſmitten of the Lord fo. 39.</item>
               <item>Vayn ſhadowes of men fo. 47</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>W.</head>
               <item>Why ther is a diuerſity in the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhementes of the reprobate and non in the rewarde of the elect and choſen. foli. 65</item>
               <item>Who thei be that can ſing the new ſonge. foli. 70.</item>
               <item>Why the true electe are called vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines foli. eodem.</item>
               <item>What it is to folowe the lambe whether ſoeuer he goeth. fo. eodem</item>
               <item>Who the be that ſtorme at the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne of predeſtination. foli. 2.</item>
               <item>We ought not for the feare of men to hyde the truth fol. 3</item>
               <item>What ſcope or marke we oughte to ſhote at in ſettinge foorth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of iuſtification of fayth. fo. 3.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:12849:86"/>
               <item>What it is to be iuſtified by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. fo. eode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </item>
               <item>What it is to be iuſtified by fayth. folio. 6.</item>
               <item>What fayeth Abraham was iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by. fo. 7</item>
               <item>What be the meanes whereby we are iuſtified or deliuered frome the ſtate of dampnation. fol. 11.</item>
               <item>What Paul vnderſtandeth by the workes of the law. fo. 14.</item>
               <item>What they muſt do that wyll en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioye the righteouſneſſe of Chriſte. folio 15.</item>
               <item>What credyt ought to be geuen to the enemis of the truthe and what ſhamful ignoraunce thei be wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in. fo. 19.</item>
               <item>Whye the ſcrybes and Phariſees were vtter ennemies vnto the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. fol. eodem</item>
               <item>Whye our greate rabbies wil not acknowledge theyr errour. fo. 20</item>
               <item>We ar not deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſins to this end that we ſhould walow in them agayne. fo. 23.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:12849:86"/>
               <item>Why the Athenians woulde here Pauls doctrine. fo. 29.</item>
               <item>Why the ſpirit of Chriſt is geuen vnto them that be iuſtified, fo. 34.</item>
               <item>Whereof the enemies of the truth be aſhamed. fo. eodem</item>
               <item>Why man was created. fo. 35.</item>
               <item>Why we be regenerate in Chriſt. folio. 36.</item>
               <item>Who they be that are offended at the doctrine of iuſtification of faith folio. 36.</item>
               <item>Whiche be the true good workes that God doth require of vs. fo. 41</item>
               <item>Whye the good workes of mercye are ſet moſt chieflye foorth vnto vs folio. eodem</item>
               <item>Whiche be the good workes that god hath prepared for vs to walke in. foli. 42.</item>
               <item>Whye all they that doe thoſe good workes that God hath commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his word do not deſerue the prayſe of well doing. fo. eodem</item>
               <item>Why fayth is likened to a ſparke. folio. 45.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:12849:87"/>
               <item>Wherin our iuſtification doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyſte. foli. 5.</item>
               <item>What cauſeth Turkes and Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimes to abhorre Chriſts religion folio. 46.</item>
               <item>Whether our good workes be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto God or not. fo. 47.</item>
               <item>Whether our good works ſhal be rewarded or not fo. 49.</item>
               <item>We are all debters vnto god. fo. 51</item>
               <item>Woorkes of ſupererogation are blaſphemous and iniurious to the merits of Chriſt and therfore they oughte rather to be called workes of derogation. fol. 55.</item>
               <item>Whereupon they grounde them ſelues that do appoynte diuerſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es or degrees of glorye in the lyfe to come. foli. 59.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>Here endeth the Table.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:12849:87"/>
            <p>¶<hi>IMPRYNTED</hi> at London, by Ihon Cyſdale, and are to be ſolde at his ſhoppe in the vpper ende of Lombard ſtrete, in All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hallowes churchyard, nere vnto grace churche. 1561.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
